<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true liberty &amp; dominion of conscience vindicated, from the usurpations &amp; abuses of opinion, and persuasion</title>
            <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12353944</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12353944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60064</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52357)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60064)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 643:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true liberty &amp; dominion of conscience vindicated, from the usurpations &amp; abuses of opinion, and persuasion</title>
                  <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Newcomb, for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] In the Savoy :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Nalson, Prebendary of Ely. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England.</term>
               <term>Conscience.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:60064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Martii 30. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR <hi>Hic Liber</hi> (<hi>cui Titulus,</hi> The True Liberty and Dominion of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. Sill, R. P. D. Hen. Epiſc. Lond. à Sac. Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60064:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE Liberty &amp; Dominion OF Conſcience Vindicated, from the USURPATIONS &amp; ABUSES OF OPINION, AND Perſuaſion.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. xx. ver. 27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Spirit of a Man is the Candle of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>In the SAVOY,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Newcomb,</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the <hi>Three Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:60064:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60064:2"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>The Introduction. <hi>Pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>Of the Reaſon why there are ſo many Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Conſcience; and of the Advantages they make of it, to promote their Intereſt, and favour their Deſigns. <hi>Pag. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Of the great Influence, which true Conſcience has upon all the Affairs of Humane Life; and therefore the great neceſſity there is, that all men ſhould be rightly informed concerning it. <hi>Pag. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Some neceſſary and univerſal Principles laid down, upon which Conſcience depends, and according to which it acts. <hi>Pag. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:60064:3"/>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Of Conſcience, its Deſcription, what is its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Employment; and the manner of its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Pag. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>The occaſion of thoſe Differences amongſt us, about matters of Conſcience, proceeds from the miſtake of Opinion, and private Perſuaſion for Conſcience. What Opinion is, and what Perſuaſion? and how they differ from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? <hi>Pag. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>How far Men are obliged by <hi>Opinion,</hi> or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Perſuaſion;</hi> and what influence theſe have upon Humane Affairs. <hi>Pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>The Differences betwixt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all Diſſenters, brought into Examination, by the forementioned Rules of <hi>Conſcience, Opinion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion. Pag. 60</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:60064:3"/>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>The pretences of Diſſenters, that their ways of Government are the best, and to be preferred before Epiſcopacy, examined and tried by the ſame Rules abovementioned concerning indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Things and Actions. <hi>Pag. 74</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. X.</label>
               <item>Of the manner and circumſtances of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and how from being indifferent, they may become neceſſary to be done, and obliging to Conſcience. <hi>Pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Of the Way whereby indifferent things become obligatory to Conſcience, not only upon a Mans private Perſuaſion, from the forementioned Rules, but ſo as to oblige all perſons who live under <hi>Government,</hi> viz. by the <hi>Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>Commands</hi> of <hi>Lawful Authority. Pag. 98</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>Some Conſiderations, ſhewing the unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:60064:4"/>and impracticableneſs, of the deſires of thoſe perſons, who, under pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, are for erecting new wayes of Church-Government, or for Toleration or Liberty of Conſcience. <hi>Pag. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIII.</label>
               <item>A vindication of what is before laid down as a fundamental Principle in this Diſcourſe: <hi>viz.</hi> That God Almighty made Mankind for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent End; that is, his Glory; and in order thereunto, by obedience to his Commands, their own happineſs both here in this Life, and hereafter in the Life of Immortality. <hi>Pag. 125</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XIV.</label>
               <item>Some neceſſary Corollaries from the former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; with the Concluſion, to all Men to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor after Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. <hi>Pag. 135</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60064:4"/>
            <head>THE <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E LIBERTY</hi> AND DOMINION OF Conſcience.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Excellency of humane Nature, that all its Actions are the Effects of Choice, and not of Chance: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly addreſſed to ſome determinate End; this End is alwayes Happineſs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60064:5"/>either Real, or at leaſt that which Men believe to be ſo. Now for the more certain attainment of whatſoever kind or degree of Happineſs Men deſire, they alwayes propoſe to themſelves, ſome Way or Rule, by which, they may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and ſteer the courſe of their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Endeavours; which otherwiſe (like a Veſſel in the midſt of the main Ocean without Charts and Compaſs,) muſt be left to the mercy of all Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and have only the bare poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of uncertain Hazard, to conduct them to their wiſhed Port. From hence it is, that there is no Art nor Science, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral nor Mechanical, but in the firſt place propoſes neceſſary Rules, for the direction of thoſe who are to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or inſtructed therein, in order to the accompliſhment, or attainment of their deſigned End. Now wherever there is ſuch a Rule, in regard there are many wayes of Error, though, but one of Truth, and that nothing is more Natural than for Men to Err;<note place="margin">Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num est errare.</note> by not attending to, or acting according to the Rule; there is a neceſſity of ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judge, who, by an impartial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, ſhall judge all humane
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60064:5"/>Actions, whether they are according to the command and direction of the Rule; and, by conſequence, whether they are right or wrong, in order to the End which is propoſed and deſigned. This Judge in the Affairs of the World, ſuch as are Life, Honour, Riches, Fame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is the determination of Reaſon, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the beſt of every Mans know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding. In the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Religion, it is called <hi>Conſcience.</hi> This is that univerſal Monarch, whoſe Ubiquitary Throne is eſtabliſh'd in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mortal Breaſt. To this the ancient Heathens owe all that little ſence they had of Religion and Virtue. 'Tis this that makes the zealous Muſsleman adore the falſe <hi>Arabian,</hi> and his ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Alchoran.</hi> 'Tis this, has raiſed the <hi>Roman</hi> Mitre to its Triple height; and in ſhort 'tis <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that has rent ſo many puiſſant Crowns, from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Univerſal and Infallible Chair. Not that all theſe powerful Effects, have proceeded from a Conſcience rightly informed, but on the contrary, many of them from a moſt barbarous and ſtupid Ignorance of the beſt Rule, by which Conſcience ought to judge, and Men to act.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60064:6"/>
               <p>However, this does moſt manifeſtly demonſtrate, the Sovereign and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial ſway, which even a pretended and imaginary Conſcience challenges in the management of all Humane Affairs.</p>
               <p>It is beyond my Province as much as it ſurpaſſes either my power or hopes, in the following Papers, to think of regulating thoſe mighty Evils, which from the want of a right meaſure of what is matter of Conſcience, and what not, have overſpread the face of the whole Earth: and I ſhall arrive at the moſt happy period of my deſign, if I can do ſo charitable a Subject as this is, ſo much reaſon, as to inform ſome, and convince others of my dear Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that hitherto, they have laboured under ſome dangerous miſtakes, in this great concern of Conſcience: the fatal effects of which miſunderſtandings, we have by the moſt deplorable experience been too deeply ſenſible of already; and ſtill lie under juſt apprehenſions, by reaſon of the great diviſions and diſtractions of mind, which daily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail and increaſe amongſt us, that the ſame, or (if poſſible) a worſe Iliad of Tragical Miſeries may be repeated over again.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60064:6"/>
               <p>Happy were that <hi>Moſes,</hi> who could ſtand in this gap; and by ſeaſonably interpoſing his charitable endeavours, ſucceſsfully repair thoſe diſmal breaches in our Holy Church, which threaten that glorious Fabrick (and with it the State, which are embarqued in one common bottom) with Ruine and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
               <p>The Sincerity of my Intention, free from Paſſion and Animoſity, as from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Partiality; the Excellency of the Deſign, which is the Publick, and by conſequence the particular good of every Perſon; the preſſing Neceſſity of our preſent Affairs; and the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and almoſt incredible advantages which may ſucceed; as they gave the firſt motion to my thoughts, ſo they ſtill give me encouragement to hope the beſt, and that our wound is not incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Certainly, if there be any Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> to heal the ulcerated Sores of the miſerable People of theſe Nations, it muſt be ſuch a Medicine, as will unite us into one common Principle, whereby thoſe miſtakes, and miſunderſtandings, the principal occaſion of all our dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, may be removed for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60064:7"/>preſent, and prevented for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe Perſons, whoſe Religion is their Intereſt; Zeal, Malice; and Gain, Godlineſs; thoſe Proſelytes of <hi>Demetrius;</hi> I am not over-confident, that this will be accepted of by them, as a Bill of Divorce, between them and thoſe gainful Perſuaſions, which they have ſo unluckily eſpouſed: however, Truth will prevail, and may convince, where it cannot convert.</p>
               <p>But if they be reſolved to raiſe Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roars for their dear <hi>Diana,</hi> they are out of my Sphere; and muſt be left to the Town-Clerk, the Secular Power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe, and convince with ſuch coercive Arguments, as indeed are more fit for them, becauſe more powerful than any that can be drawn out of all the Arce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of Truth or Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60064:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Reaſon why there are ſo many Pretenders to Conſcience, and of the Advantages they make of it, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their Intereſt, and favour their Deſigns.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere has nothing made a greater noiſe for ſome Years paſt, in this our little <hi>Engliſh</hi> World, than loud Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors about Matters of Conſcience, for Liberty of Conſcience, Toleration and Indulgence to Tender Conſciences. Nor is it leſs obvious, how groſly and notoriouſly Conſcience has, by ſome People, been abuſed. There will appear no occaſion for wonder at all this, to any perſon who does but conſider, what incredible advantages have been made of that ſingle Word. I will not recount the proſperous Wickedneſſes of the late unhappy Times, in which the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Actors and Contrivers, were obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to that great Name, for the moſt of their Victories, Glory, Fame and Riches, and all thoſe unhappy Triumphs and Trophies which they did erect upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60064:8"/>the woful Ruines both of Church and State: but let us conſider the preſent advantages which are made of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Conſcience is a keen and two-edged Sword; a Weapon both offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and defenſive; and indeed nothing cuts ſo deep in vulgar minds, who are moſt apt to be afrighted with awful ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of what they leaſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. With this Weapon it is, that all Diſſenting Parties in their Religious Wars, arm and fortifie themſelves one againſt another: with this reſiſtleſs Sword, they make no more to untie the moſt ſolid Arguments from Scripture or Reaſon, than once 'tis ſaid the young <hi>Alexander</hi> did of the famous Gordian Knot; who untyed that with his Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter, which he could not effect with all his Curioſity. 'Tis with this victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sword they conquer and ſubdue; and 'tis with this they do preſerve their conquered Proſelytes. I mean onely the Name.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Conſcience is a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible ſhield, a ſure defence againſt all the blows of Adverſaries: ſo that though Nature, Art, Eloquence, nay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60064:8"/>and Scripture too, do all conſpire to bring the moſt combined Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth and Reaſon againſt them, the mighty blow ſhall be prevented from doing execution, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon this <hi>Aes triplex,</hi> this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulnerable Target; and 'tis no more but ſaying, <hi>It may be ſo as you ſay; but it is againſt my Conſcience, and therefore I cannot believe or do as you would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Conſcience is a certain <hi>Aſylum,</hi> an impregnable Sanctuary and defence againſt all accidents. Hither, as to their laſt refuge, all Diſſenters retreat ſecurely, and are at as much eaſe, and in as undoubted ſafety, as if both Heaven and Earth were entred into the ſtricteſt League, Offenſive and Defenſive (as they think they are bound to do) to protect and defend them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, This is a never failing Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in times of ſuffering; and has a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret virtue to ſweeten that, which of it ſelf is moſt bitter, and inſupportable to all the world. Thus an Opinion that it is for Conſcience, can make the juſteſt and ſevereſt of humane puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60064:9"/>to paſs over the pallate, with the ſugar'd relliſh of Perſecution for the Goſpels ſake: Thus Death, though the deſerved merit of Rebellion and Treaſon, has, by ſome, been ſtyled Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom; and the ſuffering Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Death thought meritorious both here and hereafter. Nay, ſo ſtrangely have ſome men been blinded with the opinion of acting for and by Conſcience, as to pronounce Divine Vengeance,<note place="margin">Ireton.</note> Mercy; ſo that a villanous Contriver and Acter of Murder and Rebellion,<note place="margin">O. Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel.</note> and an infamous Regicide and Uſurper, though one taken away by the immediate ſtroke of God, the Sword of the deſtroying Angel; and the other dying with all the agonies of Mind and Body, ſhall yet be ſaid to be gone to God, and taken away from the evil to come; and, which exceeds all belief, by the blaſphemous Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of a Poſthumous flattery, ſhall be affirmed, to rival the moſt glorious Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and be ſet on the right hand of the Majeſty on high.</p>
               <p>For theſe and ſuch like reaſons it is, that all Parties, of whatſoever perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, pretend to ſo great a ſhare and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60064:9"/>intereſt in Conſcience. Upon this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as they perſuade themſelves, they build the Pile of all their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and from the Dictates of this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed infallible Guide, it is that they receive their Principles, and to which they conform their Practiſe. Ask a Quaker, why he will ſhew no reſpect or reverence to his Superiors? Why he will not take a lawful Oath before a lawful Magiſtrate, though for the manifeſtation of truth, the end of ſtrife, or the vindication of injur'd inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence? Why he admits of no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metns? or about any other of his Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents. Demand of an Anabaptiſt, why he will not allow Infants under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel the ſame priviledge they did enjoy under the Law, though he muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Goſpel a better Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? Inquire of a Presbyterian, why he ſtarts at the Surplice and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies? and any Sect, why they ſeparate from the Communion of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Shew them all the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Union, both as to Religion and Policy; demonſtrate all the dangers and inconveniences of ſeparation: and yet for all you can ſay, after all their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60064:10"/>wild, roving, and unconcluding Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, Objections, Scruples, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations, to winde themſelves off from the main point; when they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves forced from one of their ſtrong holds to another, and at laſt ſtraitned by the prevailing ſtrength of unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable and Dilemmatical Reaſon; the reſult of all ſhall be, that they are not ſatisfied in Conſcience; or that their Conſcience will not give them leave, to believe or do this or that to which you would perſuade them. Though after all this, I doubt not to make it appear, that the greateſt part of thoſe who talk ſo loud about Conſcience, I mean the Vulgar, who have little to ſay for themſelves beſides that, do ſcarcely underſtand the Word, and are abſolute ſtrangers to the true ſenſe and meaning of the thing.</p>
               <p>That ſuch therefore as are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be wilful, may be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and that they may not give to this pretended Conſcience a greater So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty, than ever God almighty did deſign the true one, by ſetting it up as an Omnipotent Idol in their hearts, I offer this following Diſcourſe; which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60064:10"/>if peruſed, with that ſobriety and impartiality of conſideration, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Concern of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may, I hope, conduce much to the preſent ſatisfaction of many, and the publick advantage of my Native Countrey; by removing the occaſion of ſo many heats and animoſities, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and diviſions, as draw their original principally from theſe miſtakes about matters of Conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60064:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the great Influence which the true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience has upon all the affairs of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life; and therefore the great neceſſity there is, that all men ſhould be rightly informed concerning it,</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving now ſhewn the great power of a pretended Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; before we proceed any further, it will be requiſite to ſhew, of what concern it is for all men rightly to underſtand themſelves in this affair of Conſcience: which cannot be better done, than by diſplaying the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Influence, which Conſcience chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges in the management of all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Actions. We will therefore brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trace it, through its vaſt Dominions of Oeconomicks, Ethicks, Politicks, and Divinity.</p>
               <p>We will begin then with private Families, and there we ſhall find Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be the onely bond of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the onely maintainer and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of thoſe reſpective Duties, which are owing from one to another,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60064:11"/>in thoſe little primitive Societies of Mankind: And therefore we ſee where this bears the ſway, there is always the moſt Domeſtick peace, concord, and tranquillity; on the contrary, where this Principle is wanting, neither the obligations of Nature, Education, or Reaſon, are powerful enough to keep men within the limits of their Duty: but <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall imbrue his hands in the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood of his onely Brother <hi>Abel: Amnon</hi> ſhall commit a Rape upon his beautiful Siſter <hi>Tamar: Abſalom</hi> ſhall rebel againſt, and endeavour to depoſe his Father: in ſhort, without a ſenſe of the Obligations of Conſcience, the Maſter of the Family will be unkind to the Wife of his boſome, cruel to his Children, tyrannical to his Servants: The Wife will be falſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; the Children will be undutiful and unnatural; the Servants will be negligent, faithleſs, and diſobedient; and all extremely vitious: And, in a word, there will be neither Order, Government, Peace, nor any kind of happineſs, in theſe little Communities, without Conſcience.</p>
               <p>If we ſtep out of private Doors into
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60064:12"/>the wider World, we ſhall find, that without the ties of Conſcience, to oblige men to their ſeveral and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Duties, there would be no ſuch thing as Virtue to be found in all Humane Race: and one might as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully ſeek, and, it may be, more probably find, Temperance, Chaſtity, Juſtice, Fortitude, Prudence, Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, Fidelity, and Gratitude, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſavage Inhabitants of the Woods and Deſarts. Without this, men reſign themſelves up ſo wholly to the conduct of their blind Paſſions of Luſt, Hatred, Anger, Jealouſie, Fear and Deſpair, that they ſeem not onely diveſted of all Morality, but even of Humanity it ſelf. Let the late diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered Inhabitants of the Weſtern World atteſt this truth; amongſt whom, for want of this, there was ſo little to be found of Morality, that had it not been for Humane ſhape, and, amongſt ſome of them, the name of Religion, it had been impoſſible to diſtinguiſh them from the ſo nearly related Brutes; ſome of which want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed little advantage of them, but a Language to expreſs themſelves in, ſo as to be underſtood.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60064:12"/>
               <p>But leaving theſe barbarous Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if we come where Morality has civilized, and common neceſſity has united men into Combinations and Societies; where there is the beſt eſtabliſh'd Government, the moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and excellent Laws, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the common good, and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring every mans particular Intereſt and Property: yet ſtill the great Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to theſe Laws, and this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt be Conſcience: which ſeems to have been the Reaſon, why all the antient Lawgivers, in imitation of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> have pretended a familiarity, and frequent intercourſe with the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and therefore propoſed their Laws to the People, as the will of the Gods, as being well aſſured, that no other Principle was capable of laying ſuch a powerful Obligation to Duty and Obedience upon the minds of men, as ſuch a belief. For all Obedience muſt be reſolved into one of theſe Principles, Hope of Advantage, Fear of Puniſhment, or Conſcience of Duty to God. Now if either Hopes of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, or Fear of Puniſhment, are the onely Inducements to Order and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60064:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60064:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60064:14"/>Obedience; leſs degrees of this Fear, or however a belief that they are out of the reach of puniſhment; or greater, though onely hopes of private advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ſhall cancel all the Obligation to Humane Laws, and the publick advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and, like an impetuous Torrent, ſhall violently break all the banks of Laws and Government, and tear up the foundations of whatever does oppoſe its furious rage. Nor was there ever any popular Inſurrection, Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or Rebellion, in any Nation, but took its original from one of theſe tempeſtuous Principles. Whereas on the contrary, no hopes of Impunity from Humane Laws, no private Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or Ambition, can perſuade a man from that Duty which he ows to Laws and Government, upon the account of Conſcience; nay, we have further ſeen, that Cruelty it ſelf, with all its terrors and tormentors, has not been able to ſhake men off from this firm and ſolid foundation of fixed Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee Conſcience the beſt preſervative againſt the threatning dangers of Inteſtine Miſchiefs; nor is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60064:14"/>it leſs available againſt Foreign Force. For unity of mind, which is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and natural effect of Conſcience, is certainly the greateſt policy, as well as ſtrength, of any People; whereas Diſcords, Diviſions, and mutual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, give all the hopes and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements to a Foreign Power to invade, and all the helps and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to ſubdue. This made the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Eagles</hi> ſtretch their victorious Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions over the greateſt part of the World; the civil Diſſentions of their Neighbours amongſt themſelves, made many potent, and otherwiſe invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble People, become an eaſie Quarry to their ambitious Arms: And whilſt, with a ſhew of Juſtice, they pretended to eſpouſe the Quarrel of the weaker part, by overpoiſing of the Ballance, both ſides, at laſt, became their prey, and thruſt their own necks under the fatal yoke, which, by unity, they might eaſily have avoided. It is to this the <hi>Ottomans</hi> owe the prodigious ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of their prevailing <hi>Creſcents,</hi> which had either never been ſo, or had long ſince been in their Wain again, if the Diviſions amongſt the <hi>Chriſtian
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60064:15"/>Princes</hi> had not given them thoſe great advantages againſt themſelves. And if we conſult the Hiſtories of all Times, Places, and Nations, we ſhall find, that no People can bid fairer for their own ruine, or give a ſtronger invitation to their Enemies, than by their own Diviſions and Diſſentions. Nor did any Government ſuffer a diſſolution, without theſe foregoing, and too often fatal Prognoſticks, of its approaching Fall; <hi>In ſe magna ruunt</hi> —</p>
               <p>Now there is nothing can beget, maintain, and preſerve this neceſſary Unity, like the Principles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This is that which cements mens Souls together with ſo cloſe and indiſſoluble an union, as nothing is able to divorce them from, but what ſeparates the Soul and Body. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets true Love, and real Friendſhips, Knots never to be looſed, but with that of Life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let us take a ſhort turn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Confines of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and there we ſhall find, that the Conſciouſneſs which men have to themſelves, that they owe an indiſpenſible duty to <hi>God,</hi> as their Great and Almighty <hi>Sovereign</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60064:15"/>and Creator; and to all Mankind, as their common <hi>Brethren,</hi> is the onely true foundation of all the <hi>Religion</hi> in the World. Without a due ſenſe of the firſt of theſe, men are Atheiſts; without the ſecond, they are worſe than Beaſts; without them both, they would be worſe than Devils, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, though it makes them tremble.</p>
               <p>So that it appears, that without this inward Principle of Conſcience, there would be neither Honeſty, Fidelity, Juſtice, Civility, Morality, Policy, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or Divinity in the World, this being indeed the Foundation-principle of all theſe; and all other things without, but inducements, and perſuaſives to Goodneſs; which men may reſiſt, and (though not without difficulty) overcome; but till they can flie from themſelves, they ſhall never be able wholely to ſubdue, and conquer all the power and influence of Conſcience: or though they may be ſo hardy to rebel againſt it, yet can they never be able to eſcape its Tortures and Puniſhments, but that of the Poet will be an univerſal truth,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60064:16"/>
                  <q>
                     <list>
                        <item>—Hostu</item>
                        <item>Evaſiſſe putes;<note place="margin">Juvenal. Sat. <hi>13.</hi> prope fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> quos diri Conſcia facti</item>
                        <item>Mens habet attonitos, &amp; ſurdo verbere caedit</item>
                        <item>Occultum quatiente animo tortore fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellum?</item>
                        <item>Poena autem vehemens, ac multo ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior illis</item>
                        <item>Quas &amp; Caeditius gravis invenit &amp; Rhadamanthus,</item>
                        <item>Nocte, diéque ſuum geſtare in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore teſtèm.</item>
                     </list>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Well rendred into <hi>Engliſh</hi> in thoſe few words of the wiſeſt King <hi>Solomon, A wounded Conſcience who is able to bear?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 18.14.</note> For let men ſay or do what they pleaſe, this Imperial Principle will rule in the minds of men, either with the <hi>Golden Sceptre,</hi> or the <hi>Iron Rod.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60064:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Some neceſſary and univerſal Principles laid down, upon which Conſcience de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, and according to which it acts.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>PHiloſophy tells us, <hi>Corruptio opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi eſt peſſima;</hi> the beſt things abuſed, become the worſt: there is no poiſon ſo invincible, as that which comes compounded with a Cordial, which by its treacherous agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the deluded palate, obtains an eaſie admiſſion, and a ſpeedy paſſage to the vital Spirits. It is therefore the common Intereſt of all Mankind, to endeavour after a true and right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of this Principle, which does ſo univerſally influence all their Lives and Actions. That we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take a true meaſure of it, it is requiſite that we conſider of ſome common Principles, which are to be found in the minds of men; whether innate or traditional, it matters not; for from theſe, Conſcience derives its Original: upon the belief of theſe it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60064:17"/>does depend: and according to theſe, if it be permitted its native liberty and freedom, it always acts.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe is, That there is one <hi>Supreme Being,</hi> which is the firſt cauſe of all other <hi>Beings</hi> in the World. And this is that which under various names and notions, has yet in all Ages, and amongſt all Nations, paſt for the moſt bleſſed, eternal, and by all to be adored <hi>Deity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, That this <hi>Supreme Being</hi> is of a moſt perfect and excellent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, infinitely happy in Himſelf, ſo as nothing can add to, or diminiſh his abſolute and eternal Felicity. This was the Antient and Univerſal belief of the World concerning the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> Nay, <hi>Lucretius,</hi> a man not over kind to that which he calls <hi>Gravis Religio,</hi> endeavours to eſtabliſh his <hi>Demi-Atheiſm</hi> upon this foundation: that the <hi>Divine Nature</hi> being tranſcendently happy within it ſelf, ſince it could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive neither addition, nor diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, therefore did not concern it ſelf with the management of the affairs of the World; as appears by thoſe well known, and too much abuſed Verſes of his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60064:17"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Omnis enim per ſe Divûm Natura neceſſe eſt</l>
                     <l>Immortali aevo ſummâ cum pace fruatur</l>
                     <l>Semota a noſtris rebus, ſejunciáque longè:</l>
                     <l>Nam privata dolore omni, privata perîelis,</l>
                     <l>Ipſa ſuis pollens opibus, nil indiga noſtri</l>
                     <l>Nec bene pro meritis capitur, nec tangitur irâ.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, That according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his Nature, his Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, he made all things, and Mankind eſpecially for a moſt excellent End.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That this End was prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the manifeſtation of his own Glory, in his Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs. Secondarily, and in order thereunto, the Happineſs of all his Creatures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral capacities, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only here in this World, or if they be capable of it, both here and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a future ſtate.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That therefore there is a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate after this life.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, That in that future ſtate, there are Rewards and Puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſeveral Poſitions, have a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral dependency and connexion one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, and are ſuch, as have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, if not univerſally been believed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60064:18"/>in the world, or at leaſt by the far greateſt part, beſt and moſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of men: and indeed they are ſuch Truths, as no man can deny any one of them, without the manifeſt danger of ruining all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Now from theſe common Notions, theſe neceſſary Conſequences follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That all the Creation, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Nobler parts of it, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly Mankind, owe, unto this moſt excellent Being, all Duty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſuch ſervice as they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of and he requires.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It follows that all the whole Creation, and particularly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, ought, according to their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ability, to promote the great Ends of the Creation, which are the praiſe and glory of the great, good, and wiſe Creator, and the happineſs and well-being of the whole, and every part: And for this, Man may go to School to the inanimate Creatures, who all perform their obedient ſervice, with the moſt punctual and exact decency and order, both for his praiſe, their own preſervation, and the happineſs of the Univerſe: according to that of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60064:18"/>Royal Pſalmiſt, <hi>Fire and Hail,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 148.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Snow and Vapors, Stormy Winds fulfill his Word, and praiſe his Name;</hi> ſtrictly obſerving thoſe Laws which at firſt he did impoſe upon them.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it follows from the juſtice and power of this excellent Nature, that thoſe parts of the Creation, which do, in obedience to his Will, endeavour to promote thoſe excellent Ends and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of his Glory in the happineſs of the Creation, ſhall, as the Reward from his Bounty upon their Obedience, be made partakers of that happineſs they are capable of, and which, in his wiſdom, he ſees beſt for them both here and hereafter: And that thoſe parts of the Creation, who, in oppoſition or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſo great goodneſs, excellency and power, endeavor to croſs, hinder and obſtruct theſe great Ends of the Creation, ſhall therefore be miſerable, both here and hereafter, by the want of that happineſs; as alſo, by ſuch other penalties as the greatneſs of their Crimes deſerves, and their Natures are capable of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60064:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Conſcience, its Deſcription, what is its proper Employment; and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of its Operation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving ſhewn what Principles are the foundation of Conſcience, <hi>viz.</hi> a ſence of that Duty which we owe to God, and to one another. The next inquiry muſt of neceſſity be, how theſe Duties are to be performed, ſo as they may be agreeable and acceptable to thoſe to whom we are to pay them. And herein common Reaſon obliges us to believe, that we are bound to follow the directions of the <hi>Supreme Being,</hi> ſo far as he has been pleaſed to manifeſt his Will and Pleaſure to us. Amongſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> has alwayes been taken for this <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Direction,</hi> as being the <hi>Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Will of GOD.</hi> And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever does ſeriouſly and attentively conſider the ſcope of thoſe Sacred Writings, muſt of neceſſity confeſs them to owe their Original to the Divine Nature, ſuppoſing it ſuch as has before
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60064:19"/>been deſcribed, and univerſally believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for all their Commands, Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Exhortations, are directly level'd at theſe great and glorious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the moſt excellent Spirit, by promoting his Glory, and the happineſs of Mankind, both here in this life, and hereafter in the life to come. So that now having found we owe a Duty, and having likewiſe found a Rule for our direction, how we ought to perform this Duty, there will be no great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to find what Conſcience is; for it is no other thing than that Principle which judges whether we have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged our Duty according to this Rule, and theſe Directions.</p>
               <p>I do purpoſely avoid the Niceties of the Schools, as too full of Curioſity, and not at all conducing to my deſign, which is to avoid all intricacy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexedneſs, and to give ſuch an eaſie, proper, and natural deſcription, and notion of Conſcience, that every man may find it in his own breaſt.</p>
               <p>Conſcience therefore, is that Power which every Man hath within his own mind of judging all his thoughts, words and actions, whether they are agreeable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60064:20"/>to that which is the beſt Rule, by which they ought to be directed. Thus from a belief that there is a <hi>GOD,</hi> and from the commands in <hi>Scripture</hi> to worſhip Him, and Him onely, my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or Power that I have of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf, immediately informs me, that I ought not to neglect his Worſhip, or to give it to any Creature: If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do either wholly, or in part omit it, or miſplace my Worſhip, my Conſcience tells me, I have done amiſs, becauſe I have not followed the direction of the Rule. Thus from the belief, that I ought to contribute all I can, to the accompliſhment of the great and good deſign of the <hi>Almighty Being,</hi> in promoting the happineſs of all the parts of the Creation, my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience preſently informs me, that I ought to do all the good I can in all ſenſes unto all Men: And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that therefore I muſt be careful to avoid doing any wilful injury to my ſelf, or to any other perſon, whereby their preſent happineſs may be impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or their future leſſened or prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; becauſe in ſo doing, I follow the directions of the Rule, which only is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60064:20"/>ſatisfactory to Conſcience; whoſe office is to accuſe me, if I do wrong; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and acquit me, if I do what is right, and what I ought to do. So that to make up Conſcience, there muſt be firſt, a true and exact Rule for all our actions, which we take the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be, <hi>as being,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſufficient to make the man of God wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> which I think is a ſufficiency for a Rule beyond all exceptions; and they who expect a better Rule, certainly expect another End, better, I am ſure, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: And, as before was intimated, if there were a neceſſity, it were no hard task to prove the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> in all particulars, the moſt excellent Rule for the management of all humane Actions, in order to the forementioned Ends of Gods Glory, and the Happineſs of the Univerſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, There muſt be a true knowledge of this Rule, <hi>Scientia</hi> before <hi>Conſcientia;</hi> which Prepoſition denotes only the private application of this knowledge to particular perſons and things: for this is moſt clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that I muſt firſt know this or that is to be believed, or done, and after this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60064:21"/>or that manner, before I can believe it to be my Duty, or be able to paſs a judgment upon my ſelf, that I have done well, or ill, in believing, or not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, doing, or not doing any thing, or not doing it as I ought, according to the direction of my Rule.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there muſt be an impartial and true judgment of my actions, by this Rule, that is, whether they have been according to the directions of the Rule, which is the proper employment of Conſcience, whoſe work is to meaſure my thoughts, words, and actions, and to try whether they are conformable to the Rule by which I am bound to act, and according to that judgment either to abſolve or condemn me for them.</p>
               <p>So that Conſcience, thus properly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, can only be exerciſed about ſuch things as are certainly known, and by conſequence, abſolutely neceſſary to be done, for ſuch are all and only the commands and directions of the Rule, according to that remarkable place of St. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 24.16.</note> concerning his own practice, which ought to be a pattern to all men. And herein do I exerciſe my ſelf, to have a <hi>Conſcience void of offence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60064:21"/>God, and towards Men.</hi> That is, the proper and peculiar Employ of Conſcience, is to judge and determine, whether I do my Duty to God and my Neighbour, according to what I know is his Will revealed in his holy Word.</p>
               <p>Now in regard, that upon this true Notion of Conſcience, there lies a great deal of weight; and it being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon miſtake amongſt weak minds, to take every thing which is offer'd to them as ſuch, without a due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a matter of Conſcience in the ſtricteſt ſence: I will endeavor to clear this Point, and make it appear, that Conſcience is only directly concerned about ſuch things as are certainly known, and therefore abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be believed and done, or not done.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore we will inquire into the Nature, and, as I may call it, the Eſſence of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we will examine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider its manner of operation and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all men.</p>
               <p>Now the very Eſſence of Conſcience is Knowledge, for no man can have a Conſcience to himſelf of any thing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60064:22"/>which he does not know, nor of any thing further than he does know it. For Example, I know that <hi>GOD is,</hi> and that He is to be worſhipped; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Conſcience tells me, I am obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to act according to that knowledge, and that I ought to adore him. I know that no Creature is to be worſhipped with Divine Adoration, and therefore my Conſcience tells me I ſin againſt knowledge, if I give Adoration, by worſhipping either Men or Angels, much more if I beſtow it upon the more ignoble parts of the Creation, Gold, Silver, Wood, Stone, Creeping Things, Birds, or Four-footed Beaſts. I do not certainly know whether Saints depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Life can hear my Prayers, though made to them in the moſt modeſt ſence, and in the ſame nature as I would do, if they were alive, beg of them to pray or intercede for me; and therefore, if I do not pray to them to pray for me, my Conſcience does not accuſe me of having neglected a Duty which I ought to have done, or ſinning againſt my knowledge: So that it is clear, that to Know is of the Eſſence of Conſcience, ſo that there can be no Conſcience
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60064:22"/>without it. Now <hi>Scientia eſt de certis &amp; indubitatis,</hi> all knowledge is of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and undoubted things; and this certainty, which is the foundation of knowledge, is grounded either upon the demonſtration of Sence, Reaſon, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation; and whatever I know, it is becauſe I have a certainty that it is ſuch in its own nature; either from the evidence of Sence, which cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me, or from clear and plain Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or elſe from a poſitive Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation; which proceeds from him who therefore will not, becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, deceive me, being Truth it ſelf: And therefore if the things I would know, be either in their own nature un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, as are all future contingencies, and many paſt actions of former Ages, about which I want ſufficient means of a certain information, I can have no knowledge of them; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, no obligation upon my mind, to believe them, or act according to them. But whereſoever there is a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of knowledge, either from Sence, Reaſon, or Divine Revelation, there my mind is not left at liberty; but has an obligation laid upon it, to act, or not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60064:23"/>to act, according to the commands of that knowledge. And that this is not my private opinion, but agreeable to the greateſt Truth, let the moſt learned Apoſtle <hi>St. Paul</hi> give his teſtimony, in that well known place,<note place="margin">Rom. 14. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever is not of Faith, is Sin.</hi> For by Faith there cannot be meant that ſupernatural Gift and Grace of believing to ſalvation, becauſe every thing to be known or done, is not the object of that Faith: and therefore, as appears by the <hi>fifth Verſe,</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> there he underſtands that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that full aſſurance of a mans own mind, which is no other thing but the reſult of a certainty of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what he ought to do, or not to do, and is properly oppoſed to that doubting and wavering of a mans mind, occaſioned by the want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and therefore he tells us, it is a damnable ſin to do that which I doubt I ought not; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>he that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is damned if he eat, becauſe it is not of Faith;</hi> that is, of a full aſſurance of knowledge, that what he does is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: for to ſuch a perſon, till he have a full aſſurance from a certain knowledge that it is not, it is ſin, becauſe for ought
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:60064:23"/>he knows it may be ſo; and the Rule tells him he is to abſtain from the very appearance of evil; and Reaſon tells him, <hi>Tutum est errare à dextra,</hi> it is the beſt to err on the right hand, by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from that, which I am not fully aſſured of, but it may be ſinful: and for this very reaſon the ſame Apoſtle tells us, that the occaſion of thoſe miſtakes in the Church, about eating things of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in ſacrifice to Idols, proceeded from a want of this knowledge: <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there is not in every man this knowledge;</hi> and for want of this, he tells them, <hi>their Conſciences were weak;</hi> that is, their minds were doubtful, and ſome were of one perſuaſion, others of another about it.</p>
               <p>So that knowledge being of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Conſcience, and certainty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Eſſence of knowledge, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that Conſcience properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, cannot be exerciſed, but about ſuch things as are certainly known, and therefore abſolutely neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved or done; which plainly ſhews the unwarrantable doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſome men, who impoſe many things upon People as indiſpenſible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60064:24"/>of Conſcience, which in their own nature admit of the greateſt doubt and uncertainty, and which they have no lawful authority to eſtabliſh, as obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the Minds and Conſciences of Men.</p>
               <p>But to confirm this, Secondly, let us examine the manner of operation and acting of Conſcience in all Men: Now the exerciſe of Conſcience, conſiſts in theſe two things: Firſt, I inquire with my ſelf whether I have done what I ought, or abſtained from what I ought? Secondly, I inquire, If I have done or abſtained as I ought, whether I have done it after that manner, and with thoſe due circumſtances as I ought? Now in both theſe operations, the neceſſity of them is the Rule, and the foundation of that neceſſity, is my certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that they are ſo: for thus I judge, I have done this, becauſe I certainly know in obedience to the Rule, I ought to do it: I have abſtained from that, becauſe I certainly know, that I ought of neceſſity not to do it: I have done it after this manner, becauſe I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly aſſured that this was according to the way directed by my Rule; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60064:24"/>my Conſcience, that is my power of judging my ſelf, pronounces for me, that I have done right and well: and then my Mind or Conſcience being ſatisfied, I am at eaſe and quiet within my ſelf; and this is called <hi>a good Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>peace of Conſcience.</hi> On the contrary, when I have done either what I certainly know I ought not, or but doubt I ought not to have done; or omitted what I am aſſured I ought to have done; or where I have not done what I ought to do, according as I ought to have done it, for the manner of performance, with all due circumſtances; my <hi>Conſcience</hi> tells me, I have not done well, or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my knowledge, and therefore my mind is unquiet and unſatisfied, haunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with guilt of the evil, and terrified with the fearful expectation of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and this is called an <hi>evil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> or to ſpeak more properly, <hi>a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of evil.</hi> But if there be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to act, or to abſtain, nor any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the manner and circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my Actions, I find no certainty of knowledge, and ſo no abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty within my ſelf to act, or not to act; to abſtain, or not to abſtain; or if I do
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60064:25"/>any ſuch action where I am left at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I find no neceſſity of doing it this way, or the other, but am left to my own freedom, becauſe I have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of knowledge from the Rule to determine me: ſo that if I do it, my <hi>Conſcience</hi> does not accuſe me; if I do it not, I find no uneaſie guilt to ſit heavy upon my mind for the neglect; and what way ſoever I perform it, ſtill my mind is at peace and quiet with it ſelf; and all becauſe there is no certainty of knowledge from the Rule, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no neceſſity or determination, and ſo by plain conſequence, no part of the dominion of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of knowledge is the <hi>Law of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and <hi>where there is no Law,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>there can be no tranſgreſſion,</hi> no obligation, nor afflicting guilt.</p>
               <p>Let not any perſon now think, that I have ſtraitned the Dioceſs of this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhop, or, to ſpeak without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, this Overſeer of the World; for thus far his proper and abſolute Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction does extend it ſelf: But <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> has likewiſe a collateral domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over all indifferent Actions, which is thus. All our Actions which may be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60064:25"/>done, or not done, without ſin on either part, are called Indifferent: As for example, If for my health or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I deſign to take the Air, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different whether I ride, or walk, or whether I go into that fair Field, or this freſh Meadow. Now all theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though in their own Nature free and indifferent, have yet this neceſſity upon them, that they ought to carry a reſpect to the forementioned great deſigns of God's glory, and the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Univerſe, and therefore ought to be addreſſed to thoſe ends, and managed accordingly: and if any indifferent action does not in ſome meaſure contribute to theſe ends, I am bound in conſcience not to do it: Which ſeems to be the reaſon of the great ſeverity our Saviour pronounces againſt idle words,<note place="margin">S Matth, 12.36.</note> not onely ſuch as are contrary to thoſe ends, but ſuch as by their being uncapable of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to thoſe great deſigns, are therefore ſinful and unlawful, becauſe uſeleſs and unprofitable. Thus for me to ride or walk to take the benefit of the freſh and free air, though in its own nature free, and left to my choice;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60064:26"/>yet I have this obligation upon me, that I ought to chuſe that part, which either from my own, or better judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may be thought moſt proper, and conducive to my health, that ſo I may be in a better capacity to praiſe and glorifie my Creator, for, and by the advantage of health, ſtrength, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, and alacrity of Mind and Body; and that by theſe I may be enabled, both for my own part, to participate of the bountiful happineſs, which kind Heaven has ſo plentifully beſtowed upon this life; and alſo, that I may be in a better capacity to promote and advance the happineſs of my fellow Creatures, ſo far as my power does ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſelf: and therefore in order to this, I am not to be injurious to any perſon, nor in taking the Air, to ride or walk over the eared Corn, or full grown Meadows; and all this, not onely out of an obligation to Humane Laws, or for fear of an Action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, a <hi>Clauſum fregit,</hi> or <hi>Pedibus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulando;</hi> but for Conſcience ſake, becauſe I am bound by the Rule, to <hi>do good to all,</hi> but injury to none. And this truly explains the meaning of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60064:26"/>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in thoſe two places,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether ye eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, let all be done for the glory of God.</hi> And, <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14. ult.</note> that is, Whatſoever indifferent action I do, I ought to have a full aſſurance, that it is not contrary, but conducive to this great deſign of the glory of God, in the happineſs of the Creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60064:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The occaſion of thoſe Differences amongſt us, about matters of Conſcience, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the miſtake of Opinion, and private perſuaſion for Conſcience. What Opinion is, and what Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? and how they differ from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus far I think it is clear what Conſcience is, and how far its proper Dominion does extend. Now that Conſcience thus rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, does univerſally and abſolutely oblige all men, I cannot think there are any will make the leaſt ſcruple; unleſs it be ſuch, whoſe Conſciences are ſeared with an hot Iron, and given up to that unthinking ſenſe, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of; and to thoſe who are paſt feeling, I do not addreſs my ſelf, or this Diſcourſe. But the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of our Age does not lie in this particular; we may have ſome of thoſe who have no Conſcience; but we have multitudes of others, who are ſo far from having none, that they are all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60064:27"/>Conſcience, who ſtrain at every Gnat, and make every thing a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and matter of Conſcience in the ſtricteſt ſenſe: I do heartily wiſh, whilſt they do ſo, that they do not ſwallow many a Camel, and in the end make ſhipwrack of true Faith, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and, by conſequence, of a good Conſcience. For ſuch as theſe are, were theſe Papers intended, with all Chriſtian tenderneſs and compaſſion; if poſſible to give them a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of what is ſo infinite dear and tender to them. For to my certain knowledge, as by much experience, and frequent conferences with many of them, I am able to affirm, moſt of this ſort of People, who pretend to be acted by Conſcience in every thing, are not yet able to give a tollerable account what Conſcience is: 'Tis ſomething within them, but they know not what: ſome of them, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, are ſo ſtupid, as to believe it to be ſome living thing within them, diſtinct from both Soul and Body. And I remember a Quaker, to whom I put the Queſtion a little haſtily, <hi>What was Conſcience?</hi> after he had
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60064:28"/>ſhewn his great ſurprize and ignorance, by being in every joynt a Quaker, and the firſt that ever I ſaw do the trick, he very confidently, as well as blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly told me, it was the <hi>Spirit of the Lord.</hi> I demanded if he meant the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> the Third Perſon in the <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity?</hi> To which he anſwered, <hi>Yea.</hi> Which makes me fear, that more, who are not of his perſuaſion, yet may be of his ſenſe, and believe what they call Conſcience within them, to be ſome Omnipotent thing, to which every thing ought to bow and obey.</p>
               <p>There have been, and will be in all Ages, ſome men who do ill, with a deſign and knowledge of doing ill: others there are, who do ill, with a deſign of doing well: to both theſe it is, that we may aſcribe thoſe unhappy diviſions amongſt us, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Conſcience. And had they taken half that pains and care rightly to inſtruct People what Conſcience is, that they have done, poſitively to tell them, This is matter of Conſcience, and that no man can do with a ſafe Conſcience; whilſt in truth, they were either not matter of Conſcience, in a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60064:28"/>ſtrict and proper ſenſe; or if they were, they were ſuch matter of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as all people were obliged to act in, contrary to both their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Practiſe: I ſay, had they done this which was their duty, they might have done God good ſervice, and promoted our common happineſs, by Peace, Unity, and Charity: which now, to the great diſhonour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Chriſtian Religion and true Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and irreparable miſchiefs in our Politick capacities, are almoſt grown ſtrangers amongſt us. For whoſoever ſhall, without partiality, conſider the affairs of theſe Nations, for this laſt Century, ſhall find, That <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> has introduced amongſt us the Synagogue of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> which now has more Votaries than the true Religion, and all others put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>There are two things which of late have been obtruded upon us, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorantly or maliciouſly, God he knows) under the ſpecious name of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and theſe are, <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion:</hi> To this luckleſs Mother, and fatal Daughter, we owe all thoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60064:29"/>diviſions, that ſtrife, thoſe bitter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyings, debate, variance, and, in truth, all thoſe intollerable miſchiefs, under which, both Church and State have, for many years, ſo heavily groan'd, and ſo deeply ſuffer'd. Some men, it is to be feared, out of Pride, Avarice, Ambition, or deſire of Novelty, having embraced ſuch Opinions, as were moſt ſuitable to their private Intereſt or Deſigns, preſently uſurp Heaven's Royal Prerogative, and ſtamp theſe courſer Metalls with the Divine Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> which immediately makes them currant Coin amongſt vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and undiſtinguiſhing Judgments. Theſe Opinions, countenanced by the ſucceſs of numerous Diſciples, and warranted by zealous Defenders, and over-eager Promoters, grew amongſt many into firm Perſwaſions; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been rooted by long continuance, and naturalized by Cuſtom, then they muſt be matters of Conſcience, then they muſt be obliging to all, and give indiſpenſible Laws to all: then they are to be defended, and maintained with Life and Fortune, and ſupported with no leſs rigorous Penalties than
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60064:29"/>
                  <hi>Eternal Damnation,</hi> to all thoſe who will not fall down and worſhip this golden Image of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will therefore endeavor to ſhew, what Opinion, and what Perſuaſion are; and how they differ from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> how far they do oblige; and wherein their lawful right and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in the management of humane Actions do conſiſt.</p>
               <p>Let us act like Men and Chriſtians, with prudence and juſtice; let us <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars, <hi>and to GOD the things which are GODS;</hi> let us not blindly, injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and dangerouſly, transfer the <hi>Title, Dignity, Power,</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the immediate <hi>Vicegerent</hi> of our <hi>Almighty Sovereign,</hi> unto theſe two <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> who, in reality, are but his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will begin therefore with <hi>Opinion,</hi> as being the elder of the two: And that you may know, that it is far infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior unto <hi>Conſcience,</hi> this is the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption which the learned <hi>Aquinas</hi> gives of it, <hi>Opinio eſt diſpoſitio ad Scientiam,</hi> it is a diſpoſition to Knowledge; that is, <hi>Opinion</hi> is an imperfect degree of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60064:30"/>Knowledge, where ſtill there is a liberty to doubt or ſuſpect that this or that <hi>Opinion,</hi> may not be exactly true: As for Example, that the <hi>Sun</hi> ſhines at high Noon, this is demonſtrative knowledge; but becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> when it ſhines, does communicate both light and heat; that therefore the <hi>Sun</hi> is a vaſt Globe of Fire, this is but <hi>Opinion;</hi> becauſe it may be ſo, and it may not be ſo. Or that the <hi>Moon</hi> is peopled with Inhabitants, is but <hi>Opinion,</hi> becauſe being capable of doubt; I can have no way to aſcertain my ſelf, of the truth of either of theſe, whether in reality, the <hi>Sun</hi> be a Ball of Flame, or the <hi>Moon</hi> another habitable Region: ſo that <hi>Opinion</hi> is that private judgment which a Man makes of things or actions which are of an indifferent nature, without any certainty of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, where he wants the aſſiſtance of ſome rule or way, and means, to attain to ſuch a certainty. And that I may not give only inſtances of Philoſophy; thus, that there is ſuch a place as Hell, the reſidence of the <hi>damned,</hi> is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of knowledge, as being of <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> beſides that it is founded upon the reaſon of rewards and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60064:30"/>in a future eſtate: But whether the Fire of Hell be material, or ſigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or both, theſe are matters of <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi> and it is indifferent to believe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or both, becauſe I am not poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly directed to believe either of them, more than the other; neither if I do believe one of them, rather than the other, is any other Man obliged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, upon my affirmation of one part to be my <hi>Opinion;</hi> but is ſtill left at his liberty, ſo he believe any, to follow that part of the <hi>Opinion,</hi> which to him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears moſt robable; and the reaſon is, becauſe I want a certain <hi>Rule</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine me, there being no Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of it, nor any way or means to attain to a demonſtrative knowledge of it; and further, in its own nature it appears indifferent, whether thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Flames be material, or figurative, or both; ſince whatſoever they are, <hi>God Almighty</hi> is thereby able to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his deſign, which is the puniſhment of the fallen Angels, and ſuch of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as muſt there be eternally miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and tormented, becauſe they would not accept of happineſs upon Gods terms and conditions.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60064:31"/>
               <p>Come we now from <hi>Opinion,</hi> to <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion;</hi> which, as before was ſaid, is the <hi>Child of Opinion:</hi> and is nothing more but that belief, which a Man embraces of any <hi>Opinion</hi> in indifferent things or actions, which are undetermined, by any certain way, or rule of knowledge, where the mind follows that part which appears moſt probable and likely to be true; ſo that in <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> as well as <hi>Opinion,</hi> there is no abſolute certainty of knowledge to determine the mind, only Men ſit down with that as a deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination for the preſent, which carries the faireſt appearance of Truth, and with that reſt ſatisfied; though ſtill they reſerve to themſelves a liberty to change their <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> ſo ſoon as a clearer evidence, or better way to find out the Truth about which they are uncertain, offers it ſelf unto them. Thus to one Man, the flames of Hell appear moſt probably to be mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial ſire, becauſe the Bodies of the damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as their Souls, muſt be there moſt exquiſitely tormented, and for that purpoſe, he thinks this ſort of ſire moſt proper; and therefore that part of the <hi>Opinion,</hi> paſſes with him into his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion.</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60064:31"/>To another, who conſiders that the condemned Spirits, and Souls of Men which are of an immaterial ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, muſt there be puniſhed as well as their Bodies, a figurative Fire appears moſt probable, and that is his <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi> To a third, who conſiders, that both Souls, Bodies, and the wicked Spirits, muſt have their ſhare of pain and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both a ſigurative and material Fire ſeem moſt agreeable to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and therefore that is his <hi>Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the difference between <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> ſeems to be no more than this, whil'ſt I embrace, with an equal indifference, either part of a doubtful thing, it is but <hi>Opinion.</hi> When from the greater probability, I paſs to a determination of my mind, then it is my particular <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The difference between matter of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and matter of <hi>Opinion,</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> is, That what is matter of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is alwayes certainly known, and therefore abſolutely neceſſary to be believed or done, or abſtained from. What is matter of <hi>Opinion,</hi> or <hi>Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60064:32"/>is not clearly and certainly known, but admits of doubting, and therefore is not abſolutely neceſſary, but in its own nature indifferent to be believed or done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60064:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How far Men are obliged by <hi>Opinion,</hi> or private <hi>Perſuaſion;</hi> and what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence theſe have upon Humane Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving now ſhewn what <hi>Conſcience, Opinion,</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> are, and how they differ one from another; it follows in the next place, that we ſhew how far theſe two laſt do oblige any perſon in the management of humane Actions relating to <hi>Divinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, every Man is obliged by his private <hi>Opinion</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in things indifferent in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and undetermined; which is the proper ſphere of their activity, to act, or not to act; to believe, or not to believe; ſo far as in acting or believing, he does not contradict a known <hi>Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which is an abſolutely neceſſary Duty. Now the great and general Rule of all our Faith and Actions, being Gods Glory, and, in order to that, by our Obedience to his Commands to that purpoſe, to promote the happineſs of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60064:33"/>the Univerſe, both here and hereafter, it is very eaſie for any perſon, in any part of his Belief, or in any of his Actions, to ſee whether they have a reſpect to theſe ends; for if they have not, they certainly croſs the great deſign and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of our <hi>Almighty Creator,</hi> to whoſe <hi>Will</hi> we owe all ready Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and then, by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, they become abſolutely unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Thus ſuppoſe I am of <hi>Opinion,</hi> for very good and religious conſiderations, that I ought to keep one day in the week a voluntary day of <hi>Faſting</hi> or <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence,</hi> and I chooſe <hi>Monday</hi> as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different day; I am obliged by my own private <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> to keep that day ſo; but neither my <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> nor <hi>Example,</hi> can have any influence to oblige others to do ſo, who are not of the ſame <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion</hi> with me: But if either a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from my lawful <hi>Superiors</hi> forbid me <hi>Abſtinence</hi> on that day, or enjoin it to be obſerved as a <hi>Feſtival;</hi> or if I find, that by <hi>Faſting</hi> I impair my health or ſtrength, I am then obliged to obſerve it no longer as a day of <hi>Faſting,</hi> becauſe then my private <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> would croſs a certain known <hi>Rule of Conſcience,</hi> by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60064:33"/>diſobedience to <hi>lawful Authority.</hi> And I ſhould alſo be injurious, both to my ſelf, and, it may be, to many others, who may have a dependance upon my life and well-being; whereby I ſhould act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Will of God,</hi> who would have me, by all lawful and prudent wayes and means, to promote my own happineſs even in this life; and all theirs, with whom I have a Concern, ſo far as I am able by juſt and honeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors.</p>
               <p>Secondly, every Mans private <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> obliges him ſo far, as in the determination of his Belief, and Actions, it follows the better, more ſure, and warrantable part. Now the better, and more warrantable part of our judgment and determination in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things and actions, is firſt, that which has the Conſent, Judgment, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, Example, or Practice of the beſt Men, in all Ages, as neareſt to the neceſſary Rule of Life and Actions. But becauſe this cannot ſo eaſily be known, or found out, eſpecially by the unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ordinary ſort of People, who have neither opportunity nor ability to diſcover what the Judgment and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60064:34"/>of the beſt Men in forepaſt Ages has been, by ſearching the Hiſtories and ancient Records of former Times; therefore ſecondly, that is the better, more ſure, and warrantable part of our <hi>judgment,</hi> in indifferent matters of <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> which follows the judgment of <hi>Charity, Peace, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and, by ſo doing, contributes moſt to Gods glory, by promoting the happineſs of all Men, both here and hereafter: for theſe are univerſal Rules, and known Commands, and therefore neceſſary to be obſerved, being given us for the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and management of our Actions in general. Now there is no Man that has the free uſe of his Reaſon, and will make uſe of it, but may eaſily diſcover, whether any of his Actions are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or contrary to theſe <hi>Rules,</hi> and this great End.</p>
               <p>So that it appears plainly, how dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent the <hi>Obligation of Conſcience</hi> is, from that of <hi>Opinion,</hi> or <hi>Private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion. Conſcience</hi> obliges all Men, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, at all times, and in all places, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally and abſolutely, they being known, evident, and certain Duties, which are thereby commanded. <hi>Opinion</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60064:34"/>and <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> oblige only ſome private Perſons, in ſome Caſes, and at ſome Times, and never further than they have a juſt reſpect to ſome general <hi>Rules of Conſcience,</hi> in regard they are not ſo certainly known, but that they may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Doubt, and have a poſſibility of being other than they appear, or are thought to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60064:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Differences betwixt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all Diſſenters, brought into Examination, by the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Rules of <hi>Conſcience, Opinion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT is a Divine, as well as Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Truth, <hi>Rectum est menſura ſui &amp; obliqui,</hi> a right Line ſhews both its own ſtraightneſs, and the crookedneſs of that which is oblique: Having therefore ſhewn this <hi>Rule of Truth,</hi> and which I have not in the leaſt endeavoured to warp or bend, ſo as to ſit any private or ſiniſter deſign of my own, or of any Party; let us now lay it to the Work, and it will quickly diſcover, who are <hi>the Workmen that need not be aſhamed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15. 1 Cor. 3.12, 13, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>who have rightly divided the Word of Truth;</hi> and <hi>have built upon that good foundation, Gold, Silver, precious Stones, in beauty far ſuperior to the poliſhed cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Temple:</hi> And who are they, that have built Straw, Hay, and Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſuch combuſtible ſtuff, as has ſet the glorious Fabrick of the <hi>Church</hi> into
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60064:35"/>flames of <hi>Contention,</hi> and which to the loſs of the Builders, muſt be burnt up; though they themſelves may be ſaved, ſo as by fire, provided they did it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and not of malicious wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet their work muſt periſh.</p>
               <p>We will therefore conſider the moſt material, and chief things, which are in difference amongſt us, and, by an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial applying of this <hi>Golden Rule of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> ſee who come neareſt the Truth and Right.</p>
               <p>I do purpoſely avoid the knotty <hi>Queſtions of Divinity,</hi> and the different <hi>Opinions</hi> about them, in regard, that theſe may be diverſly believed and maintained without breach of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi> and I know there are, and have been many eminent Men in the Church of God, who have wholly differ'd in their judgments, about ſome abſtruſe Points of <hi>Divinity,</hi> without prejudicing the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> either of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State:</hi> in regard they defended them only as their private Perſuaſions, and were both too modeſt, prudent, and charitably honeſt, to diſturb the Peace and Quiet of the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to impoſe their particular
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60064:36"/>judgments in things not clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as neceſſary <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Practice,</hi> upon the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of all other Men.</p>
               <p>The main and grand Differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all thoſe who have ſeparated themſelves from her Communion, ſo far as I am able to diſcover by the Writings of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Parties,</hi> are either about the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> it ſelf, or about the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and manner of <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there ought to be <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> I ſuppoſe all <hi>Parties</hi> will readily acknowledge, becauſe a great Apoſtle tells us, <hi>God is the God of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not of Confuſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God;</hi> by which it is plain, that that is no <hi>Church of God,</hi> which is not under <hi>Government;</hi> or which counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <hi>Confuſion;</hi> and therefore the ſame Apoſtle abſolutely commands, <hi>That all things be done decently, and with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> The thing that is complained of, is, That this way of <hi>Government,</hi> by the <hi>Epiſcopal Hierarchie,</hi> being no where in plain, and poſitive Words, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, thus ſet down, ordered, and eſtabliſhed in <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60064:36"/>
                  <hi>Rule of Conſcience,</hi> therefore it ought not to be impoſed tyrannically and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſly, upon Men of weak and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Conſciences;</hi> eſpecially, when an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and better way of <hi>Government,</hi> more agreeable to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Primitive Simplicity</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is now found out, and diſcovered. For though <hi>Government</hi> in its own Nature be abſolutely neceſſary, yet where <hi>God</hi> does not interpoſe any <hi>poſitive</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or Directions, as he did concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> there this or that <hi>Government</hi> are equally indifferent, and the beſt is to be choſen and preferred before the reſt.</p>
               <p>How weak a Plea and Refuge this is, to call for and expect plain and expreſs Words, Commands, or Directions from <hi>Scripture</hi> for every thing we do or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, every Man muſt acknowledge who does but conſider, that we owe even the Belief of ſome of the Articles of our Faith to conſequences from <hi>Scripture,</hi> and not to plain, poſitive, and expreſs words: As for Example, that of the Myſtery of the <hi>Glorious Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, three Perſons, but one God;</hi> which words are not to be found in all the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60064:37"/>
                  <hi>Holy Canon.</hi> How much more unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable is it then, to expect expreſs Words and Commands of <hi>Scripture</hi> for <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> which is of a far more inferior Concern than <hi>Faith?</hi> And how dangerous a matter it is, to admit of this Propoſition, <hi>That nothing is to be believed or done, for which there cannot be brought a clear and poſitive place of Scripture,</hi> let all Chriſtians judge: And whether, if it were as heartily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, as it is by ſome Men vigorouſly preſt, it would not root out the very foundation of all <hi>Religion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we will join iſſue with them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Point, and give them a fair tryal at the <hi>Bar of Conſcience,</hi> their own <hi>Judge,</hi> upon their own <hi>Aſſertion:</hi> If therefore <hi>Government,</hi> being undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by <hi>Scripture,</hi> be indifferent whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this or that; and the beſt to be preferred; How ſhall it be determined, and by what Authority, which way of <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> is the beſt? For till there be ſuch a determination, as before has been made appear, it can be no more than <hi>Private Opinion,</hi> and therefore can lay no more <hi>Obligation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Mans <hi>Conſcience</hi> to yield Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60064:37"/>to it, than any other particular Perſuaſion does, which can only oblige thoſe who are of the ſame Perſuaſion, and only ſo long as they continue ſo, and no longer, nor any others who are not ſo perſuaded; and therefore by the <hi>Rule of Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> are free, and ought not to be impoſed upon, for fear of wounding their <hi>tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences;</hi> which is the direct and ready way to have as many ſeveral <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> and <hi>diſtinct Churches,</hi> as there are Men of <hi>ſeveral Minds</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſions</hi> about which is the beſt; it being certain that if Men be left to their <hi>liberty,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man abounding in his own ſence, will eſteem beſt of his own way, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Proverb, <hi>Every Crow will think his own Bird faireſt;</hi> which, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> at laſt muſt amount to <hi>Anarchy,</hi> inſtead of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> and <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> in the room of that <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> which God expects and requires in all his Churches. For the <hi>Scriptures</hi> leave it in ſuſpence, and at leaſt are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent as to moſt particularities of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> there being no more plain and expreſs words for any ſort of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which any of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60064:38"/>would eſtabliſh, than there are for that againſt which they contend; and all <hi>Parties</hi> will plead the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſpeak as much, or more, for their way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, than for any other.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore try who will have the advantage, and bid faireſt for ſuch a determination, as ſhall oblige all mens Conſciences, according to the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Rules, how any indifferent matters of <hi>Opinion</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> (ſuch as the Queſtion in diſpute muſt be, according as they have ſtated it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary and obligatory to all mens Conſciences.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, we have reaſon to believe, that the way of Government now eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is the beſt, becauſe we find it does not contradict any known Rule or poſitive Command of Scripture; but, on the contrary, all its Commands, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, Doctrine, and Practiſe, are founded upon, and derived, if not from plain words, (as moſt of them are) yet from moſt evident ſenſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of Scripture; which, as before was intimated concerning the Articles of Faith, are as obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60064:38"/>to Conſcience, as Scripture it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This way of Government, as it is now eſtabliſhed, appears to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the better, more ſure and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table part of our Judgment, in indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, ſo as to make them become obliging, and that in both its branches; <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, it is agreeable to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Approbation, Example, and Practiſe of the beſt men in all Ages, from the Apoſtolick times, as will be evident to all, who ſhall, without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, peruſe the Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where there are many not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect traces and footſteps of this way of Government, ſo far eſtabliſhed, as the Powers of the Heathen Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who then had all the Civil and Temporal Juriſdiction, would permit. But there is a whole Cloud of <hi>Witneſſes</hi> for it, in the univerſal conſent, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, approbation, and defence, of all thoſe holy men from the Apoſtles times; who though not divinely inſpired, yet were men of ſuch eminent Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity and Piety, as would not permit them to write any thing directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Primitive truth, which ſome of them did immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60064:39"/>from the mouths of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Lord; and many of them were ſuch, as by Martyrdom did, with their deareſt bloud, ſet their Seals to the teſtimony of Jeſus. Such who lived in thoſe Ages, before <hi>Rome</hi> and her Biſhops ever thought of uſurping the Title of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and therefore cannot be thought guilty of any combination with them, in erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or impoſing this way of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> upon the <hi>Chriſtian World.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The Determination of the Judgment, that this way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the beſt, follows the better, more ſure and warrantable part, <hi>viz.</hi> the Judgment of Charity, Peace, and Unity: Charity, with the firſt, beſt, and paſt Ages of the Church, who all lived and died under obedience to this way of Government; of all which glorious Martyrs, Saints and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, it were the moſt uncharitable opinion to judge and condemn them, as being guilty of living and dying in, defending, maintaining, and practiſing a way of Government, altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable and contrary to the Word and Will of God; as all Diſſenters
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60064:39"/>would perſuade the World, whilſt they tell them, this Government is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful and Antichriſtian. It follows likewiſe Peace and Unity, both with that part of the Church which is now Triumphant, and with the Univerſal Church Militant, over all the World, who, except ſome few of the Diſciples of <hi>Calvin,</hi> all agree in this way of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, We have reaſon to believe this way of Government to be the beſt, in regard that it does more, than any other whatſoever, promote the great deſigns of the glory of Almighty God, and the happineſs of mankind, here, by Piety, Peace, Juſtice, and Unity, in order to their eternal happineſs hereafter; following herein the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Commands, and Example of the bleſſed Jeſus, and his holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, without turning to the right hand or to the left.</p>
               <p>Beſides, We have other very ſtrong inducements to perſuade us, that this Government in the Church is the beſt, as being that which by Gods own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and approbation, was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the very infancy of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60064:40"/>Church, by the Divinely inſpired Apoſtles; and for this belief, theſe, amongſt many others, are very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and perſuaſive Reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The great bleſſings which God has imparted to the World under this way of Government by Epiſcopacy; for it is notoriouſly known, that all the World, which did embrace the Chriſtian Faith, received it with, and from this Government.</p>
               <p>Secondly, which is very remarkable, and a confirmation of the former; It is impoſſible to find any Church, which wears an antient Name, and pretends to be of Primitive Converſion to the Faith of Chriſt, but how much ſoever they may have degenerated in other things, yet ſtill they retain this way of Government: witneſs the <hi>Roman, Greek, Armenian,</hi> and even the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Ruſſian</hi> and <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Churches, who though in other matters they differ as wide in Opinion, as in Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, which, according to the Adage, is <hi>toto Coelo;</hi> yet in this they do all moſt harmoniouſly agree, retaining both the Name, Dignity, and Office of Biſhops, as the Governours of the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60064:40"/>Church amongſt them: And I do not know any one thing, excepting the Canon of the Holy Writings, which contain the Fundamentals of our Faith, which Heaven has appeared ſo ſolicitous to preſerve unaltered and uncorrupted, as this way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the whole Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, This very argument, which with ſo much pomp and triumphant ſolemnity, is perpetually, by all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, urged as invincible and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable, if it be well examined, will depoſe plainly for Epiſcopacy, and that there is no poſitive Rule or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in Scripture for it, is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrong, and, it may be, a more powerful ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for it, than they who make uſe of it are aware of. And the true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why in Scripture there is no more ſaid to juſtifie it, with the higheſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, may be believed to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with a <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> it was by an unqueſtioned conſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all thoſe, who did embrace the Chriſtian Faith; and there were none found then, nor in many Ages after, ſo impious or audacious to oppoſe or contradict it. And had there
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60064:41"/>been any thing in the Government, either unreaſonable, or contrary to the will of God, the Jews and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, whoſe hatred made them curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inquiſitive into whatſoever might appear a defect in Chriſtian Religion, would certainly, with their quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted malice, have diſcovered it, the diſcovery of which would have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported as much as they did deſire, that was the ſubverſion of the Church from the very foundation. But ſo great was the Unity of the Chriſtians in this point, and ſo excellent and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reprehenſible did the Government ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that in all the oppoſition Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion met withall, though not an Article of the Faith could eſcape their cenſures, we do not meet with any thing againſt this way of Government; and well it was there was then ſuch Unity: for could thoſe Enemies of our Religion have met with half thoſe diviſions, which now Chriſtians have made amongſt themſelves, they would certainly (without the aſſiſtance of a Miracle to preſerve it) have improved them to the utter ruine of the Church, to which there is no Road leads ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:60064:41"/>directly, as that which undermines the Goverment. In ſhort, I do heartily wiſh, that all thoſe who are ſo zealouſly, it were well if I might not ſay furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, bent and oppoſite againſt Root and Branch of Epiſcopacy, would conſider ſeriouſly at what they ſtrike, and whether they do not really af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him, who, as the Root of it, is by St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtyled, <hi>the great Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60064:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The pretences of Diſſenters, that their ways of Government are the best, and to be preferred before Epiſcopacy, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and tried by the ſame Rules above-mentioned concerning indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Things and Actions.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>LEt us now ſee any other form of Government in the Church, which can make ſo fair, ſo true, ſo juſt a plea for it ſelf as <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> has done; whether <hi>Presbyterian, Independant, Anabaptiſt, Quaker,</hi> or any other of what name or diſtinction ſoever, who diſſent from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and flie from her Communion, upon the account of the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Firſt, There is not any of theſe that can ſhew expreſs words, or commands of Scripture, for that way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they would introduce: And therefore they are unjuſt to us, whilſt they cry up their own way, and endeavour to impoſe it upon the world, as matter of Conſcience; ſince,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60064:42"/>as before has been proved, nothing can be ſo in its own nature, for which there is not a plain and poſitive command, or a natural and true conſequence, from <hi>Scripture</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or admitting their Propoſition, That all <hi>Governments</hi> being in their own nature indifferent, and the beſt to be preferred; how does theirs appear to be the beſt? I hope they are better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to common Senſe, Reaſon, and Cuſtom, than to think their own Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion or Teſtimony ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us that it is ſo; ſince the Son of God, who was Truth it ſelf, yet tells us, <hi>If I bear witneſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Joh. 5.31.</note> if he had no other witneſs: And therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>John,</hi> whom all men accounted a Prophet; to the Scriptures, which he bids them ſearch; to <hi>Moſes,</hi> in whom they truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and, in another place, to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and wonderful works, which they ſaw with their own eyes.</p>
               <p>Come we therefore to the common Rule; and it is no more but juſt, that they ſhould receive the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſtand to the determination
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60064:43"/>of the ſame Judge, to whom they have made their Appeal.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place therefore, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe ways of Government which they would eſtabliſh, with the ruine of the preſent, contradict a known Rule, nay, many plain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Scripture; for whilſt they go about to overthrow the old Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and introduce a new One, they are <hi>diſobedient to thoſe that have the rule over them,</hi> both in Church and State, whom they found veſted with that Authority, and which, for any thing they are able to prove to the contrary, was of Gods own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for ſo ſaith St. <hi>Paul, The powers that be are ordained of God;</hi> even thoſe Heathen and truly Antichriſtian Powers: how much more then the Supporters and Defenders of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith? They reſiſt an Authority, warranted with long ſucceſſion, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with many prudent and antient Laws; Laws to which they themſelves, and their Anceſtors, by their free Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives in Parliament, had given their Vote and Suffrage; and therefore, by their own voluntary Act and Deed,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60064:43"/>(and ſome of them by the ſtricter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations of moſt Sacred and repeated Oaths) they were bound with the ſtrongeſt ties of Conſcience to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in all dutiful obedience; which St. <hi>Paul</hi> enjoyns under the pain of Damnation, the ſevereſt of all the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties God Almighty can inflict up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mankind: and therefore he tells them, they <hi>muſt needs be ſubject for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in their determination, that their way or form of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the beſt, they do not follow the better, more ſure and warrantable part of judgment in indifferent things. Let them ſhew us in all Antiquity, (except ſome miſtranſlated places in the <hi>Engliſh New Teſtament,</hi> where <hi>Presbyters</hi> are falſly rendred <hi>Elders</hi>) the leaſt foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps, approbation, defence, or practice of any other manner of Government in the Church for this Sixteen hundred years and upwards, beſides the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal; if they can do this, then they may lawfully pretend, they do not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Old, but revive it, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the New Model of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but if they cannot, as I am ſure
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60064:44"/>if it could have been done, we had heard it on both ſides of our ears long before this; let them dread the fearful doom which the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt thoſe who remove the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Land-marks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 24.22.</note> and are given to <hi>change; for their calamity ſhall come ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi> Both of thoſe who fear not God, becauſe they fear not their lawful King his Vicegerent; but are given to change, delighted with Novelties and Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this their determination is far from the judgment of Charity, Peace, and Unity, either with the paſt or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Ages; and much further from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the great deſigns of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the happineſs of Mankind either here or hereafter. Let all <hi>Europe</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this ſad Truth; and particularly theſe <hi>Britiſh Iſles,</hi> which by this beſt way of Government, of ancient <hi>Albion,</hi> White and Happy, was changed into <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a diſmal Field of Blood; it were endleſs to recount what Wars, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Sacriledge, Deſolation and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Bloodſhed, and moſt unparallel'd <hi>Solemn Murder of Majeſty,</hi> the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60064:44"/>thing on earth; have been the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of endeavouring to ſet up, and eſtabliſh theſe new wayes of Church Government. And wherever any of theſe new Diſciplines did prevail, they quickly verified the Advice of young <hi>Rhehoboam</hi>'s hot-headed Counſellors, making their little Fingers, heavier than the Loins of Epiſcopacy: and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Whips, with which thoſe Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers chaſtiſed ſuch as really de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it, into Scorpions, Axes and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; nor did they ſpare either Life or Fortune that ſtood in their way, or durſt oppoſe them: And this was the true reaſon, why even thoſe perſons, who were ſo violent againſt Root and Branch of Epiſcopacy, notwithſtanding their <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> yet their Wiſdom, Fear, or Policy, would never give them leave to eſtabliſh <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery,</hi> which they found a Government ſo imperious, abſolute, and inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Nor is this fair and honeſt dealing, in Diſſenters; to pretend that becauſe all ſorts of Government are indiſſerent, therefore why ſhould not theirs be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen which is the beſt? when by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60064:45"/>we have found the contrary, and in the mean time not to allow ours a bare indifferency: but to perſuade their credulous Followers, with the greateſt confidence, That our way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Biſhops, is <hi>Popiſh, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures;</hi> and that their own way is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them, and the Primitive Diſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line of the Church; and therefore as a matter of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the main mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too, the one to be avoided, and the other to be embraced by all thoſe who hope for <hi>Salvation of their Souls.</hi> That Cauſe (though it be the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi>) betrays it ſelf to be very weak, which is to be ſupported by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, feeble, and Corner Arts and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as Pagans, and Heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers would bluſh to have been found guilty of.</p>
               <p>As for that common objection of theirs againſt <hi>Lord Biſhops;</hi> we will eaſily grant them, that the Primitive Clergy did not abound in Tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; but then, they had ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, as, I believe, none of theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will be willing to gratifie the moſt beloved of their Paſtors withall, when
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60064:45"/>
                  <hi>they who had poſſeſſions ſold them, and laid down the price at the feet of the Apoſtles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4, 34.</note> to diſpoſe of as to them ſeemed moſt ſit. This would be a hard ſaying, who would bear it? nor indeed could it be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, as the affairs of the World ſtand at preſent. But theſe Honours which the preſent Clergy do enjoy, being Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, are not by us believed to be at all eſſential to the Office of a Biſhop, and are only annexed by the bounty of Princes, as are alſo their Eſtates, for the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſupport of the Rank they are in, for the encouragement of Learning and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for the advantage of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, as it is a Politick Society of Men. And they may as well maintain a Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Principle, and quarel with all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Eſtates that are above theirs, as with theſe; for if any Temporal Eſtate or Dignity may, by free Gift or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, divolve upon a Church-man, why not theſe? And that this may happen without offence or ſcandal, beſides the experience we have had in an Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Peer of this Nation, who,<note place="margin">Earl of <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </note> not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years ago, from a private Prieſt, by ſucceſſion, came to the Honour of one of the firſt Earls in <hi>England.</hi> I appeal to themſelves, who would think it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60064:46"/>the greateſt injuſtice, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their being Churchmen, to loſe a good Temporal Eſtate from their Anceſtors, or a Barony, either by Deſcent, or Royal Bounty. Beſides, let all men judge, if this would not be the way to furniſh us with <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Prieſts, of the meaneſt and loweſt of the People, not onely for Birth, but Learning, Parts, and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: And what a diſcouragement it would be to the Gentry and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who, by their Generous Birth, Advantageous Education, Noble Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, and many other Excellent Circumſtances and qualifications, are fitted by the great influence they may have both upon the Prince and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to do both the Church and Sate the moſt conſiderable Honour and Service? I am afraid few of them would addict themſelves to the more ſerious and painful Studies of Divinity, if by their devoting themſelves to an immediate attendance upon God's Altar, they muſt caſt off the Entail of Temporal Honours and Eſtates from themſelves. Nor does this derogate a little from the ſuperlative Bounty and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60064:46"/>Goodneſs of the Divine Nature, to think, that he who does ſo plentifully, frequently, and freely beſtow theſe Honours and Eſtates, as bleſſings, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all other Conditions of men, ſhould prohibit and deny them to thoſe, who have voluntarily obliged themſelves to his peculiar Service, and upon whom he is pleaſed to confer the excellent Title of his <hi>Ambaſſadors;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> and therefore moſt certainly does allow them honorably, ſo as to be able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Dignity of ſo high a Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter: eſpecially ſince they have his Royal word and promiſe for it,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> 
                  <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour.</hi> Prince and Prieſt, were not by God thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent under the Law, in that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which he himſelf conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and eſtabliſh'd. And therefore one word in the Hebrew Language ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſies both.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And till ſuch time as he is pleaſed to declare his mind to the contrary, I know not upon what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence any man ſhould divorce thoſe two, which he had once made one. Neither by virtue of theſe Lordſhips, do Biſhops Lord it over Chriſts Flock, as by the ſcoffing wantonneſs of ſome
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60064:47"/>men (who ſhould be more ſerious, than to be witty at the expence of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture) they are ſaid to do: ſince it is clear, that their Temporal Baronies give them not the leaſt influence upon Church affairs, more than they give unto the other Noble Peerage of the Realm. And the Juriſdiction of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, as a Biſhop, and a Biſhop as a Baron, are as wholly diſtinct, as that of a Lord of a Manor, or any other Lord is from the power of a Biſhop in his Dioceſs.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, <hi>A Biſhop muſt be given to Hoſpitality;</hi> how ſhall he be able to do that without an Eſtate? If he muſt have an Eſtate, he muſt be Lord of it, for ſo is every man of what he does poſſeſs: and if it ſhall be thought fit by Royal Authority, the Fountain of Honour, to add to that common Right, a more particular and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Title of Honour, that may offend ſome mens Ambition or Envy, but can never be found to be either diadvantageous to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hurch or State, or contrary to the Scripture, the <hi>Rule of Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60064:47"/>that no other way of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Church can really pretend to thoſe advantages, which may make an indifferent thing become neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and obliging to Conſcience, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Epiſcopal; by which it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that to ſubmit to this Form of Government, as it is now eſtabliſh'd in the Church, is ſo far from being againſt a good Conſcience, that no man can reſiſt it, without ſinning againſt Conſcience, ſince it has all the qualiſications which are neceſſary, for the making an indifferent thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obligatory to every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which all the other pretenders want: <hi>viz.</hi> It comes neareſt to the <hi>Rule of Scripture,</hi> it follows the better, more ſure and warrantable part of our judgment; it anſwers all the ends of Government, by promoting the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and contributing to the happineſs of mankind here, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Peace, Unity, and Concord; and hereafter, by teaching, commanding, and practiſing true Piety and Holineſs. And it is evident, that to diſſent from this Government, can never be the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but of <hi>Opinion</hi> or
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60064:48"/>
                  <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> neither of which can lay any obligation upon mens minds, which is abſolute and indiſpenſible, as before has been made moſt evidently appear.</p>
               <p>I wiſh that all Diſſenters would ſeriouſly reflect with themſelves, whilſt they do ſo violently cry up Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and pretend it for their ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whether they have not abuſed themſelves and the World, in miſtaking <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion</hi> for it? of which they may eaſily be ſatisfied, by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial application of what has before been ſaid of this particular.</p>
               <p>After all this, we ſhall difficultly be perſuaded to relinquiſh the Plea of a Divine Right in Epiſcopacy, for which ſo much reaſon has been, and may be brought to prove it; and upon which we ſhall have occaſion briefly to touch hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60064:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the manner and circumſtances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip; and how from being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, they may become neceſſary to be done, and obliging to Conſcience.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus have we ſeen, that though private and falſe <hi>Opinion,</hi> or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced and miſtaken Perſuaſion, and, it may be, malicious Deſign and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, combined with diſcontented En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, may be loud and clamorous againſt this Government of the Church, by the excellent and antient way of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy; yet Conſcience is ſo far from being againſt it, that it is wholly and clearly for it. Let us now come to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the manner of performance of Divine Worſhip, which has occaſioned no ſmall ſtirs, tumults, and diviſions amongſt us.</p>
               <p>And here likewiſe I ſuppoſe, that all Parties do thus far agree, that there ought to be ſome Modes and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in the Worſhip and Service of God; that is, ſome Time, ſome Place, ſome Words, Geſtures, Poſtures, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60064:49"/>Habits, for the performance both of Publick and Private Worſhip, which Conſcience tells us we are bound to pay unto Almighty God. Herein likewiſe I ſuppoſe, that all Parties are agreed, that theſe things, or however, ſuch of them as are in controverſie amongſt us, are, in their own natures, indifferent; and therefore properly the ſubject of Opinion or Perſuaſion: and were there no determination on either ſide, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Duty of Worſhip were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, it might be done this way or the other: And from hence likewiſe it appears, that no Circumſtance of Religious Worſhip, is in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſimply unlawful, becauſe no where in Scripture prohibited, either in direct words, or by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: ſo that no mans Conſcience can be juſtly offended by the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any of them, ſince <hi>where there is no Law, there can be no tranſgreſſion.</hi> Let any Diſſenters therefore ſhew, either a poſitive command, or a plain conſequence from Scripture, why I ſhould not ſerve God in a ſet form of Prayers and Praiſes? or why I, or any other perſons, ſhould not perform all
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60064:49"/>the ſeveral Offices in the Book of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service mentioned? Why ſuch Geſtures, Habits, or Signs ſhould not be made uſe of? And then ſomething is ſaid to make them unlawful; then every man, in point of Conſcience, would be obliged to abſtain from them: but till that be done, they will remain in their own natures ſimply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and ſo far lawful. And ſo long as they are ſo, which will be to the Worlds end, they act falſly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, who endeavour to perſuade weak minds, (and ſuch as are not able to Judge) that theſe Circumſtances of Religious Worſhip, now in uſe in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are abſolutely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, and that they ought neither to uſe them, nor to have any commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with thoſe who do uſe them; which is the true reaſon and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſeparation. And that the treacherous dealers deal thus trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly with us, is plain; for that the Ignorant and Vulgar always make this their Plea, for their forſaking our Communion, that their Conſciences will not give them leave to joyn with us in our unlawful Ceremonies, as, in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60064:50"/>deriſion, they call all the Service of the Church. And this they muſt needs have from their Teachers, who either ought not to have been Teachers, if they themſelves were not come to the knowledge of the Truth; or if they were, they ought to have taught them the Truth; and that theſe Modes, or Circumſtances of Religion, being in their own natures indifferent, were onely matters of <hi>Opinion,</hi> and not of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> until ſuch time as they were, ſome way or other, lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. And to prove that this they ought to have done, and more than this, have taught their Hearers, That they ought to have ſubmitted to ſuch determinations, I will endeavour to make it plainly appear, by ſhewing how indifferent Circumſtances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip become obligatory to Conſcience, and ſo neceſſary to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>Now all indifferent Circumſtances in Religious Worſhip become neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, if in general they anſwer the great Deſign of God's glory, and the Happineſs of Mankind, both here and hereafter: it were enough therefore
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60064:50"/>to demand, which of all theſe indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things are contrary to theſe great Deſigns, and wherein? which I am ſure it is impoſſible for them to make appear. But for the ſatisfaction of ſome, who may retain their prejudices, for want of a better information, I will ſhew more fully and diſtinctly, how indifferent things become neceſſary; with ſome ſhort reflections upon ſuch of them, as in the Ceremonies and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are moſt objected againſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, an indifferent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance in Religious Worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes neceſſary, if in general it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to the advancement of Piety and Holineſs; becauſe whatſoever does ſo, is abſolutely neceſſary to be done; and it is every man's duty, to endeavour to promote goodneſs, by all lawful ways and means. Thus therefore, ſet and appointed times for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God become ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; ſuch are the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and all other holy Faſts and Feſtivals, in which People aſſemble together to call upon and praiſe God, and to give him that devout Worſhip, and humble
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60064:51"/>Adoration, which in duty they are bound to do; where ſin is reproved, the ignorant are inſtructed, the weak are confirmed and ſtrengthned, the Holy Sacraments, thoſe Pledges of God's Love, and Seals of our Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Saints in Light, are ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated; and all people are exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, directed, perſuaded, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to the performance of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective duties, towards God and all men. And that ſuch ſet times are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, will appear, becauſe, were men left to their own liberty, when and where to perform theſe Duties of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, ſuch is the treachery and backwardneſs of mens natures, that if they were not determined by a neceſſity, they would generally neglect the Service of God, and find out per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual excuſes and evaſions to delay the performance of it, to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Piety and Religion, and the great hazard of the ſalvation of their Souls. For this purpoſe alſo, publick Places of Aſſemblies, decent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for thoſe uſes, become neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: and by ſuch Dedication, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn ſetting apart to the Service of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60064:51"/>God, they become his Houſes, and ceaſe to be common, or indifferent, by obtaining a Relative Holineſs;<note place="margin">Exod. 3.5. Ezek. 42.13, 14. and 44.19.</note> ſuch as did the ground about the burning Buſh, the Temple and its Veſſels, the Veſtments and Chambers of the Prieſts; all which are called Holy: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Royal Pſalmiſt does propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally tell us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 93. ult.</note> 
                  <hi>Holineſs becometh thy Houſe for ever;</hi> which muſt either be falſe, or elſe be underſtood of <hi>Chriſtian Temples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Indifferent things and Circumſtances in Divine Worſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary, if they promote <hi>Peace, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> according to thoſe great and neceſſary Rules of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Live in peace, if it be poſſible;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11. Heb. 12.14. 2 Cor. 13.2. Coloſſ. 3.14. Epheſ. 4.3. 1 Cor. 13.13.</note> 
                  <hi>as much as in you lies, follow peace with all men. Finally, brethren, be of one mind. Above all things put on charity, which is the bond of perſectneſs. Keep the unity of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the bond of peace. Now remaineth Faith, Hope, and Charity, but the greateſt of theſe is Charity.</hi> Now that one ſet and preſcribed form of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and other Religious Duties, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely promote all theſe, nothing can
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60064:52"/>be more plain: for where men are left to their own liberty, one likes this way of performance, another likes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers another way; from hence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ariſes a breach of Unity, from thence men come to Diſputations and Controverſies, which is the beſt way. And whilſt each party is equally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in the defence of their own Opinion, many heats of paſſion happen, which vent themſelves in bitter words; from thence men come to variance, diviſion, and ſeparation; from thence to hatred; and then the door is ſet wide open to violence, force, confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, war, and all the innumerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, which are its dreadful conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and conſtant companions. That theſe are ſad and experimented truths, I appeal to all ſober and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive men: but leſt their Judgment ſhould not be ſatisfactory, let us hear the judgment of an Apoſtle, who was guided in what he writ by an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit;<note place="margin">Jam. 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>But if ye have bitter envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and ſtrife in your hearts, glory not, and lie not againſt the truth. This wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſual, devilliſh: for where
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60064:52"/>envying and ſtrife is, there is confuſion, and every evil work. But the wiſdom that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits; without partiality, and without hypocriſie: and the fruit of righteouſneſs is ſown in peace of them that make peace.</hi> Nor is it poſſible to find out any way to make peace, and bring men to unity and charity, but by ſome determination of theſe indifferent things; which is not onely my ſenſe and opinion, but that of all diſſenting Parties, who therefore propoſe the determination of them, by the eſtabliſhment of their way, as the onely expedient to obtain theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ends.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Indifferent things become neceſſary, if they promote Decency and Order, becauſe ſo they are agreeable to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s general Rule,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> Thus, that all ſhould kneel at the Prayers where it is appointed; beſides, that it is a poſture of ſupplicating, humility, and devout adoration; That they ſhould ſtand up at the rehearſal of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60064:53"/>Articles of our Chriſtian Faith, and at the Hymns, Pſalms, and Praiſes, are all matters of great decency and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Whereas that one ſhould ſit, another ſtand, a third lean, a fourth lie along at his eaſe, are no leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent and irreverend, than diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and confuſed. Thus, that Church-men ſhould wear diſtinct Habits, both when they celebrate the Divine Service, and at other times, ſuch as may ſhew gravity, ſobriety, purity, innocence, or diſtinction of degrees, are all decent and orderly, and ſo far therefore neceſſary.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Indifferent things become neceſſary, if they be ſignificantly expreſſive of our inward profeſſion. Thus the Croſs after Baptiſm, the Ring in Marriage, the Surplice and other Veſtments, Poſtures and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, having all their outward ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications of the inward profeſſion of our minds, are neceſſary for thoſe ends. I ſhould ſpeak more fully of theſe things, had not the Learned Mr. <hi>Falkner</hi> taken ſuch pains about them, and ſifted them ſo narrowly,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60064:53"/>as not to leave any juſt pretence of a quarrel againſt them; to which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Diſcourſe I therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Reader, for an ample ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in all theſe particulars.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60064:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Way whereby indifferent things become obligatory to Conſcience, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a Mans private Perſuaſion, from the forementioned Rules, but ſo as to oblige all perſons who live under <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> viz. by the <hi>Determinations,</hi> and <hi>Commands</hi> of <hi>Lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus far I have ſhewn the chief, among many Conſiderations, whereby any indifferent thing may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary: ſo that if any perſon finds theſe or any other indifferent things in the Worſhip or Service of God, conduces to theſe Ends, he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged in <hi>Conſcience</hi> to the performance of them; but this layes only a private obligation, and the ſame that it does upon all other indifferent things and actions, which yet remain ſo, by being undertermined. But now in regard ſome of theſe things, though innocent and indifferent in their own Natures, may, to ſome Mens Opinions and Perſuaſions, appear very conducive to the before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60064:54"/>Ends; others may appear more effectual to ſome other Perſons: leſt from divers Opinions, about theſe Circumſtantials of Religion, which are beſt, moſt decent, orderly, and edifying, there ſhould ariſe diviſion, diſtraction, and confuſion in the Service of God, as by miſerable experience we daily find there does; it is requiſite that we ſeek for ſome ſtronger obligation whereby thoſe things which are indifferent may become neceſſary to all; and this muſt be, by the determination, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a <hi>lawful Authority,</hi> which has power to judge, which amongſt all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different circumſtances of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, conduce moſt to Gods glory, and the good of Mankind, eſpecially thoſe under their charge and juriſdiction, by promoting and maintaining Peace, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Concord, and Piety: and after ſuch judgment, to paſs a final determination, which ſhall lay the double obligation, both of a prudent and neceſſary <hi>Law,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Conſcience</hi> upon all who live under their Government, and expect the advantages of it, and therefore owe Obedience to it. For otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes and differences muſt be endleſs, if
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60064:55"/>Men will not refer themſelves to ſome Umpires and Arbitrators to decide them; which muſt (after Men have tyred themſelves to find out what theſe Arbitrators muſt be?) at the laſt be <hi>lawful Authority.</hi> Now that all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are of the ſame judgment with us in this Point, and believe that a <hi>lawful Authority</hi> has this deciſive Power, it is moſt plain, from the frequent inſtances, and repeated importunities which they make to the Supreme Authority, to make Alterations in the preſent, or to eſtabliſh another manner or form of <hi>Worſhip</hi> according to their way: or however, if they cannot hope for ſuch Conceſſions, yet they will Petition, that <hi>Authority</hi> will not interpoſe it ſelf in theſe Religious Affairs, but leave them to their freedom in the manner of the exerciſe of their <hi>Religion;</hi> and this is, if I miſtake them not, that which they call <hi>Liberty of Conſcience:</hi> And they muſt either be the greateſt Diſſemblers and Hypocrites in Nature, by begging that from <hi>Authority,</hi> which they believe it has no real Power over; or elſe it plainly implies, That it is in the Power of <hi>a lawful Authority</hi> to determine that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60064:55"/>Liberty, in indifferent things, which concern the circumſtances of <hi>Divine Worſhip.</hi> This therefore being acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, we have nothing to do but to prove, That the <hi>Authority</hi> which has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined theſe indifferent things, and by conſequence now made them neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be done, and matter of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> had a juſt Right and Power, as well as wiſe and prudent Reaſons and Conſiderations ſo to do, as being <hi>a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We muſt therefore conſider and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what is requiſite to make an <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſo lawful,</hi> as that it may of Right challenge ſuch a deciſive and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native Power, as that all Perſons who live under it, ſhall be obliged in Point of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to ſubmit to its definitive Sentence, and take it for a <hi>finalis Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia,</hi> in all indifferent things; and to which no Man can be diſobedient, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a manifeſt and wilful ſin againſt <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in the breach of thoſe known commands, <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>And let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, that <hi>Authority</hi> which is of <hi>Gods appointment,</hi> is, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60064:56"/>
                  <hi>a lawful Authority,</hi> as plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>a Divine Right from him by whom Kings reign.</hi> Such was the Authority of <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Samuel,</hi> and the Judges; and even of <hi>Saul,</hi> a wicked and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Prince, of whom therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Deſtroy him not, for who can lift up his hand againſt the Lords Anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi> And it was well for him that he fell into the hands of a Man who was after Gods own heart. We have ſeen ſome, whom a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer intereſt than <hi>Davids</hi> in his death, would have tempted to ſerve him as <hi>Epominondas</hi> did his ſleeping Centinel; had they found him ſleeping, they would have been of <hi>Abiſhai</hi>'s judgment, and have left him ſleeping his laſt.</p>
               <p>But to proceed, ſecondly, That <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is lawful, which is warranted by long Succeſſion: Preſcription</hi> is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a good and ſafe Plea and Title, for all other Men for their Eſtates and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; certainly much more for the Crowns of Sovereign Princes: for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their Title paſſes into Inheritance, which is a Right which no Man can vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate or invade, without being guilty of the breach of that poſitive and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60064:56"/>known Command, <hi>Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>That Authority is lawful, which by Choice, and common Conſent,</hi> for their mutual benefit and advantage, Men agree to, and by lawful wayes ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulate, and oblige themſelves, one or more to govern, and rule, and the reſt to obey: for this is founded upon the Law of Nature and Nations, which teaches all People, that Faith in ſolemn, deliberate and lawful Contracts, ſuch as this is, is moſt ſacredly to be kept invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated; otherwiſe there could not be any Society, Government, Law or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the World. And the Holy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings confirm the ſame, when they tell us, our ſolemn Compacts and Contracts are to be obſerved, though to our loſs and detriment, or elſe we muſt never expect to aſcend the holy and heavenly hill;<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.4.</note> except we be ſuch as though we ſwear, that is, make a ſolemn lawful Contract, though to our own prejudice in the event, and yet nevertheleſs change not, but ſtand firm to our promiſe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation.</p>
               <p>Now all theſe ſeveral wayes of any Authorities becoming lawful, ſo as to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60064:57"/>have a juſt Power and Dominion in making Laws for the determination of indifferent things, which, amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, are moſt conducive to Gods glory, and the Publick advantage of thoſe under their Dominion, both in Civil and Religious Affairs, are moſt eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be found in the preſent Authority of theſe Nations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, there is <hi>Divine Appointment</hi> and <hi>Ordination,</hi> whether we reſpect <hi>Monarchy</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopacy?</hi> And if we can prove there were Kings and Biſhops in the World, when <hi>St. Paul</hi> wirt his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, I think, notwithſtanding what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have ſaid againſt it, the Caſe will be clear;<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
                  <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there is no Power but of God;</hi> that is, lawful Powers, ſuch as the then <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, who by ſucceſſion became lawful; for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine he meant to countenance unlawful and uſurping Powers: and therefore he adds, <hi>the Powers that be,</hi> that is, the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors, and their ſubordinate Magiſtrates and Miniſters, <hi>are ordained of God, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, ſhall receive damnation.</hi> Now that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60064:57"/>there were Kings when he writ, is plain from that place, where he commands, <hi>That first of all Supplications, Prayers, Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks, be made for all Men, for Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and all that are in Authority.</hi> If <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Writings were a Rule for thoſe Ages, they are likewiſe a Rule for us, and for all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Worlds end, and then the Argument will hold good, If Kings in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s time had a Divine Right to their Crowns, they have ſo ſtill, or elſe what was Scripture then, is not ſo now; the danger of which conſequence is ſo apparent, that I cannot imagine there will be found any that will venture to own it.</p>
               <p>The great queſtion will be, Whether there were <hi>Biſhops</hi> then? For if there were, they likewiſe, by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Rule, <hi>were ordained of God,</hi> or elſe they had no Power. That there were <hi>Biſhops,</hi> it is plain, for we have the Name very frequent in <hi>Scripture,</hi> Chriſt himſelf, from whom the reſt ſo often mentioned derived their Office and Authority as before we took notice, being called <hi>the great Biſhop,</hi> as well as <hi>Paſtor of our Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:60064:58"/>
               <p>And that theſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> had a Power and Authority in the Church, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the ſame office in the Government of the Church as the preſent <hi>Biſhops</hi> do, is no leſs evident; and that in this very Point of determining indifferent things <hi>in Divine Worſhip:</hi> Thus <hi>St. Paul</hi> takes upon him to order the Church of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> about the Celebration of the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> and after that done, tells them, <hi>If there were any other thing in difference or diſorder, the rest will I ſet in order when I come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.34.</note> And that he did this by virtue of his Office, and by a Power derived from Chriſt, the firſt and great <hi>Biſhop,</hi> he tells them, <hi>That he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lord, that which he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto them:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 23.</note> And wherever he is poſitive in giving any Rules or Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Government, Decency, or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we may aſſure our ſelves he does it by virtue of this Power of his Office; for otherwiſe he would tell us, it is but his private Judgment or Perſuaſion, which he would not impoſe upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, though he had a fair pretence ſo to do, as appears by that place concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Virginity</hi> and <hi>Marriag:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Virgins, I have no Commandment
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60064:58"/>of the Lord; yet I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> But if any Perſon ſhall pretend he did this by virtue of his <hi>Apoſtolical Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> which was an immediate Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the mouth of Chriſt at his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Converſion; to convince them that a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who was no <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> had the ſame Power, and exerciſed the ſame Office, there is nothing more plain, than that place in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Titus: For this purpoſe left I thee in</hi> Crete,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>that thou ſhouldest ſet in order the things that are wanting, and ordain Elders in every City;</hi> in which place I think our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tranſlation</hi> has not rightly expreſſed the meaning of the <hi>Original Greek.</hi> And this ſeems to be the proper ſenſe of the words; that <hi>St. Paul</hi> having been him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in <hi>Crete,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> tranſlated <hi>Ordain,</hi> ſignifies to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and appoint a perſon over a certain place and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and ſet many things in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he left <hi>Titus</hi> there, to place ſuch Prieſts as he before had Ordained, in the ſeveral Cities of that Iſland; and put them into the Power and Office of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> which he had not done, as may appear by the following deſcription of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> what manner of Man he ought to be; and for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is Tranſlated <hi>Elders,</hi> it ſignifies
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60064:59"/>in all Antiquity, (the beſt Expoſitor of the Idiom of words) <hi>Prieſts</hi> who were therefore ſo called, becauſe always cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen out of the ancienteſt Converts to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and the longeſt ſtanders in <hi>Religion;</hi> and the Rule held good, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Prieſts</hi> as well as <hi>Biſhops;</hi> that in their Elections, they ſhould not chooſe a Novice; that is, one lately converted, leſt wanting the ballaſt of age, experience and diſcretion; the height of ſo honorable an office ſhould puff up ſuch an one with pride, and ſo he fall into the condemnation of the Devil. And that <hi>Titus,</hi> who was the firſt or chief <hi>Biſhop</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> as well in order of place as time,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.6.</note> and ſo had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inferior <hi>Biſhops</hi> under him, we have the Poſtſcript, or rather Superſcription of the Epiſtle, which for any thing can be proved to the contrary, may be as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as the Epiſtle; beſides, that he was the firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> in order of time, we have the teſtimony of all Antiquity, who never once doubted the truth of it.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then Powers in the World; and the Powers that then were, being <hi>ordained of God:</hi> it follows plainly, that they
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60064:59"/>have a juſt and warrantable, if not an undeniable Plea to a Divine Right.</p>
               <p>Secondly, There is long ſucceſſion of both: of this very Race of Kings for above 600 years: and long may their Imperial Crown and Royal Dignity flouriſh and increaſe; even ſo long as <hi>the Sun and the Moon endure:</hi> And for the ſucceſſion of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> it is of much an ancienter date; and though the time be not certain, yet that the <hi>Britains</hi> did very early receive <hi>the Chriſtian Faith,</hi> and with it <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> is a thing not to be doubted, if we will give any credit to the <hi>ancient Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſome of which would perſuade us, that <hi>Britain</hi> was <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as ſoon, or even before <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there is <hi>Choice,</hi> and a freedom of Election in the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> which repreſents the groſs Body of the <hi>Nation;</hi> and is one part of the <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> thereof: as for the Intereſt which the reſt of the moſt <hi>Honourable Peerage</hi> have in the management of Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, it being one of the dear bought Fundamentals of the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> it was a thing never diſputed till the late dayes of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> when the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60064:60"/>were violently torn up by the roots, with the Tempeſt, or rather Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricane of Religious Rebellion; and I hope it will never come to a ſecond Vote, that the Houſe of Peers is uſeleſs to this Nation, or a Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</p>
               <p>So that here is whatſoever is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to make any Authority lawful, ſo as to have a juſt Right and Dominion over all thoſe who live under it, for the final determination and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all indifferent things, both in Religious and Civil Affairs.</p>
               <p>That this may appear plain to every apprehenſion, we will give an inſtance in a point controverted amongſt us. Prayer is an immediate act of Divine Worſhip, and of it ſelf abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be performed to God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.2. Matth. 21.13.</note> who is <hi>the God of all fleſh, and therefore unto him ſhall all fleſh come;</hi> becauſe he <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth prayers,</hi> and his <hi>houſe is the houſe of prayer for all Nations.</hi> But to pray in a ſet and preſcribed form of words, or to pray as a mans abilities give him leave, or as it is called, by <hi>Extempore prayer,</hi> according as the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may ſeem to require, are in their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60064:60"/>own natures indifferent: and I doubt not, but if either be done with all due circumſtances, they may be acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptable to God. But now one man is perſuaded, that ſet forms in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſervice of God are the beſt, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other thinks, <hi>Extempore prayer</hi> the beſt way. So long as this is undetermined by a Lawful Authority, every man is obliged to follow his private Opinion, becauſe Conſcience obliges him to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that determination of his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in indifferent things, which he is fully perſuaded is the beſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces moſt effectually to God's glory, and the promoting of Piety. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe diverſity of Opinion, Perſuaſion, and Practice in this Duty, is apt to breed Diviſion and Diſſention; and to prejudice, if not ruine that Unity, Peace, Charity, and Order, which ought to be preſerved inviolate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all men, eſpecially Chriſtians; therefore that Authority, which has a juſt power over us, as being of God's appointment, of long ſucceſſion, and of our own choice; to prevent theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, and the confuſion and dangers which may enſue upon diviſions of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:60064:61"/>Mind, and difference of Practice, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth it ſelf: and conſidering, that our great Lord and Saviour, who tells us, he was to be our Example, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a ſet form of Prayer, and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively commanded his Diſciples ſo to pray,<note place="margin">Luke 11.2.</note> 
                  <hi>When ye pray, ſay, Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. That both the Antient and Modern Churches did, and do uſe and approve ſet Forms of Prayer in Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that hereby, raſh and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men, ſhall not have liberty to utter any thing before God;<note place="margin">Mat. 6.7.</note> nor to <hi>uſe vain repetitions, as the Heathen did;</hi> nor (which is much worſe than they were guilty of in their much ſpeaking, for which they thought to be heard) non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, indecent or irreverend expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: that men of greater abilities ſhould not be puft up, and thoſe who have not that freedom and fluency of utterance, ſhould not be deſpiſed, in regard for their Piety, ſoundneſs of Judgment, integrity of Life, or ability to Govern, they may be of as great uſe in the Church as others. That hereby the ignorant and unlearned ſhall be better able to joyn with him that Miniſtreth, knowing what he is to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60064:61"/>ſay, than if they did not; and with a ſafe Conſcience may ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> which I am ſure to every <hi>Ex tempore</hi> Prayer they cannot; and that all men may, by Uniformity, be brought to Unity, that ſo neceſſary Bond of perfection, both as to Religion and Civil Policy. For theſe, and many other neceſſary and prudent conſiderations, this Lawful Authority judges it moſt conducive to God's Glory, moſt agreeable to his Will, and moſt effectual to procure the happineſs of thoſe under their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, both here and hereafter, to preſcribe and command a ſet Form of Prayer, in the Publick Worſhip of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</p>
               <p>And now that which before was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, becomes neceſſary in point of Conſcience: becauſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> is clear in the caſe, that <hi>Lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> is to be obey'd, in whatſoever it commands, that is not ſimply and abſolutely unlawful, and that for Conſcience ſake; and the obligation which before I might have from my private <hi>Opinion</hi> or <hi>Perſuaſion,</hi> ought, in Modeſty, as well as Duty and Charity, to give way to the Determinations of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60064:62"/>my Lawful <hi>Superiors,</hi> in all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things.</p>
               <p>And therefore they who, now it is determined, either deſpiſe it, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to uſe it, or to joyn with thoſe who do uſe it, ſin againſt Conſcience, becauſe againſt many plain and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive commands of <hi>Scripture</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and for which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems extremely ſolicitous, as well knowing Pride and Diſobedience to be the moſt natural ſins: and therefore commands, that men be <hi>put in mind</hi> (as being apt to forget their Duty) <hi>that they be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Principalities and Powers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>to obey Magiſtrates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The very ſame may be ſaid of any of the reſt of thoſe things which are enjoyned, by the preſent Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Nation, which, by being commanded, from indifferent become neceſſary, and with ſuch a dreadful neceſſity, that whoſoever reſiſteth a Lawful Power, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> be to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, <hi>ſhall receive to themſelves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let them ſeriouſly take notice of it, how light a matter ſoever it may be made, there is no man who does
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60064:62"/>thus wilfully reſiſt and diſobey Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that can hope for <hi>Salvation.</hi> As for thoſe who do it in ignorance, I will not determine how indulgent God may be to them. But they muſt know, that though God may have winked at their former ignorance, yet now he commands them, and all men, every where to repent. And they will be inexcuſable, if they be ignorant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will be ſo. It is their duty therefore, to look for a better Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their minds; and laying aſide all partiality and prejudice, to ſubmit to the truth, how contrary ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be to their <hi>Opinions,</hi> which, by long continuance in, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very ſtrong and habitual to them: for without Repentance and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there can be no Pardon.</p>
               <p>I cannot, without amazement, ſee ſome men, who appear in other things moſt nicely Conſcientious, yet make ſo ſlight a matter of this; nay, many of them, the greateſt and onely diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing part of their Religion, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to diſobey Lawful Authority, and by their Example and Practiſe, if not Doctrine, at leaſt in private, to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60064:63"/>teach others to do the ſame. I wiſh they would conſider, what dangerous influences ſuch Practiſes have had, and ſtill have, upon their Bodies, Souls, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and Eſtates, and indeed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every thing that ought to be dear and tender to them. Beſides, the moſt fatal, miſchievous, and dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences they have had, and, if pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, will have ſtill upon the ſafety and well-being of the Community in which they live: which, by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to Laws, the onely Fences of Religion, Life, Right, and Property, thoſe <hi>Deliciae Humanae generis,</hi> the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of all Mankind, they do as much as in them lies to ruine and deſtroy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:60064:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Some Conſiderations, ſhewing the unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs, and impracticableneſs, of the deſires of thoſe perſons, who, under pretence of Conſcience, are for erecting of new ways of Church-government, or for Toleration or Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO ſhew the great unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and impracticableneſs of the deſires of all Diſſenters, there need no more to be ſaid, than to make them this Propoſal, which I dare ſay may moſt ſafely be done, That ſo ſoon as they ſhall unanimouſly have agreed in all particulars, and ſo as to reconcile all Intereſts, and ſatisfie all Parties, what way of Government they would have eſtabliſhed, they ſhall receive a gratification of their deſires; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in the mean time they ſubmit, as becomes good Subjects and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to the preſent. And if they ſhall, in anſwer to the offer, ſay, That it is impoſſible to find out ſuch a way of Government, as ſhall pleaſe all
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60064:64"/>Men, Intereſts, and Parties; would it not be the higheſt frenzie imaginable, by removing the preſent Government, of the goodneſs of which we have had ſo long experience, to introduce any other, which can gratifie but one, and, it may be, an inconſiderable Party; and, in recompence, diſoblige all the reſt; and, for any thing we know, even thoſe who ſo eagerly deſire it, as ſoon as any others, ſince having never yet made a full trial of it, though it may look bravely, like <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour upon <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.39.</note> it may not prove ſo eaſie or convenient, but, with him, they may be willing to put it off again, and ſtick to the old and plain Epiſcopal Armour of the Shepherds Staff and Sling.</p>
               <p>Beſides, this way of Government in the Church, is ſo curiouſly twiſted and interwoven with the Politick Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the State, that it is impoſſible to pick out this part, without ſpoiling the Beauty, and unravelling the whole Web and Frame of the Government; it is one of the main Pillars, upon which this weighty and well-built Fabrick ſtands; and cannot be taken away, but it muſt endanger the fall and ruine
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60064:64"/>of the whole Building: and they muſt be as full of revenge, and as blind as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who would, by pulling down this Pillar, bring the Houſe about their own heads; ſince it is odds, but, with him, they muſt periſh in the common ruine; and I hope, what ever will they may have, their Hair will never be ſuffered to grow ſo long again, as to recover their <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s ſtrength, ſo as to be able to effect it. It was this conſideration which made as wiſe and learned a Prince, as ever ſwayed the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Sceptre, ſo frequently tell the Diſſenters of his Age, <hi>No Biſhop, no King:</hi> which by the moſt deplorable experience, was verified in his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. Nor did the fatal conſequence end there; but after, <hi>No Biſhop, no King,</hi> came marching up a dreadful Army of Negatives, <hi>No Houſe of Peers; No free, no full Houſe of Commons; No Law, no Juſtice,</hi> unleſs it were the <hi>High Court</hi> ſo called; <hi>No liberty, no property, no ſafety, no ſecurity,</hi> and, at laſt, <hi>nothing but conſuſion;</hi> all admirable effects of changing that Government, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was moſt ſafe and eaſie, into that which was moſt Arbitrary, Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60064:65"/>and inſupportable. If experience be not ſufficiently convincing in this particular, I know not what new School of Fools, or rather Mad-men, we muſt ſeek for, to perſuade us to the belief of theſe Truths.</p>
               <p>But further, I wiſh that all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters would conſider with themſelves, whether this will lead them, and what muſt be the end of it. For a Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Diſobedience to the Commands of a Lawful Authority, is a Principle deſtructive of all Government, of all Religion, and even of that which theſe men would endeavour to eſtabliſh: for we will ſuppoſe what they deſire, that that way of Government, which they are ſo fond of, were, by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in favour of them, eſtabliſhed and ſetled as firmly and ſtrongly, as the preſent Church-Government is; it is impoſſible that it ſhould pleaſe all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nay, it is moſt certain, it would diſpleaſe all other Parties, whoſe way was either abrogated to make room for the new one, or theirs which was rejected, and in probability therefore, the greateſt part of the Nation: and there would not want thoſe, who
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60064:65"/>would be able to raiſe and manage more forcible Objections and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt their way, than any they can bring againſt what is now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Now they muſt be unreaſonable in the higheſt meaſure, if they would not grant the ſame liberty to others, who diſſent from them and their way, which now they deſire for themſelves; ſince it is not to be doubted, but they would have the ſame (and poſſibly a juſter) plea of Conſcience for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which theſe now make, and therefore ought to have Indulgence and Toleration: and I would gladly know whether that can be called a Government, or onely an Image of it, and an empty name, where men have liberty to obey it, if they pleaſe, or may be diſobedient to it by its own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, if they ſo pleaſe?</p>
               <p>But further, what reaſon can they have to expect any other, having ſhewn them the way to change, but that the Authority ſhould ſtill make trial of new Governments, and not confine all their kindneſs to them, but ſtill gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and oblige, firſt, one Party, and then another, according as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60064:66"/>who compoſe that Authority, may be favourably inclined to one perſuaſion or another? I hope they would not complain of Injuſtice in the <hi>Lex Talionis,</hi> or grumble to reſign that Power, which, for their ſakes, others before them were obliged to do. And ſhould the Wheel turn thus round, they muſt with their way expect to be laid in the duſt. And what ſtrange Alterations, Revolutions, Settlements, and Unſettlements muſt there be? What face of Government, or rather what Confuſion, muſt of neceſſity fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Practiſe of this Principle?</p>
               <p>And that theſe are the natural ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Diſobedience to Lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, let us but turn our eyes a little backward, and we ſhall plainly ſee: And theſe Diſſenters, however they ſeem to have forgot it, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they have ſeen the days, when the Presbyterian was in favour, and full of hopes, having troden upon the neck of diſmounted Epiſcopacy, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance into the Chariot of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but the crafty Independent coming ſlily behind him, whipt up his heels, and laid him in the dirt; and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60064:66"/>was juſt going himſelf to take poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the vacant ſeat, when the ſurly <hi>Anabaptiſt, Quaker, Leveller,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral others, ruſhing in all at once upon him, told him, with the Hand all the while upon the Hilts, that they had as juſt a right as he, and that they would not part with it, without a fair Trial of skill, who had the longeſt Sword? And there was nothing gave the late <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> more trouble, than the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of theſe ſeveral Intereſts, which he kept from falling foul one upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, by tollerating all for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and cajolling the Heads of the Parties with Proteſtations and Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, that in his heart he was of their perſuaſion, and, in time, would declare himſelf to be ſo: though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in regard of the Malignant Party, it did not ſtand with his Intereſt, nor theirs, ſo to do, till they were more fully aſſured againſt the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: though at laſt they all found him to be a meer <hi>Proteus,</hi> or <hi>Polypus</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that he could change him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the ſhape and colour of that Party which was neareſt to him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let them conſider, That this
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60064:67"/>Principle muſt give increaſe, growth, and encouragement to all Sects and Hereſies; ſince all pretend Conſcience, and plead for Toleration. And if this Liberty of Conſcience be granted them, there muſt of neceſſity follow infinite and unavoidable Diviſions, Separation upon Separation, Confuſion, and at laſt Atheiſm; ſince amongſt ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to the true Religion, all will at laſt come to be ſuſpected to be falſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe are certainly the neceſſary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and inevitable conſequences, of unſetling the preſent Government in the Church, either by changing it for a new one, or permitting Toleration, or what men call, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience:</hi> And we muſt either believe, that theſe Diſſenters do not foreſee, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the danger of this Precipice, to which they make ſuch haſte; or if they do, that they are the moſt malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Mankind, ſince they would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſice all <hi>Law, Government, Liberty, Property,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to their own private <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:60064:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A vindication of what is before laid down as a fundamental Principle in this Diſcourſe: <hi>viz.</hi> That God Almighty made Mankind for an excellent End; that is, his Glory; and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by obedience to his Commands, their own happineſs both here in this Life, and hereafter in the Life of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus far I have endeavoured to follow the Clue of Truth and Reaſon; which if others would like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe do, I doubt not, but it would bring them out of thoſe Mazes and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinths of doubts, which perplex their minds, and make their Lives ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie both to themſelves and others, by making many things matters and ſcruples of Conſcience, when in truth they were not ſuch. And not onely ſo, but likewiſe it would conduce much to the calming of thoſe ſtorms and tempeſts, which are gathering from ſo many ſeveral Quarters, and ſeem to threaten both Church and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60064:68"/>State, if not with Shipwrack, yet with moſt violent agitations and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>But before I conclude, there is one thing which I have laid down as a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Principle in this Diſcourſe, and upon which a great part of this weighty building of Conſcience does depend, as upon a main Pillar; which I think it will be neceſſary to make clear and evident. And that is, That the great <hi>Creator,</hi> out of the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his Nature made the World, and particularly Mankind, for a moſt excellent End; <hi>viz.</hi> his own Glory, and, in order thereunto, the happineſs of Mankind here in this Life, as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to Eternal happineſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>That this is a moſt certain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Truth, (however ſome nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-ſpirited men, who would engroſs all the Bounty of Heaven to themſelves, may think otherwiſe, by taking ſuch low meaſures of the Divine Goodneſs and Beneficence, as may be proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the Stature of their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, though far ſhort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, which is the onely true meaſure
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60064:68"/>of the Deity) I doubt not but to make it moſt evidently plain and apparent, to all thoſe who do not wilfully cloſe their eyes againſt the brighteſt beams of Truth, Reaſon, and Scripture.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, we muſt conſider the Incomparable Excellency of this Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Being, who is the Author of all things; for he himſelf tells us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.10.</note> that <hi>his mercy reacheth unto the Clouds, and his goodneſs far above theſe viſible Heavens;</hi> and that it <hi>is over all his works.</hi> And leſt we ſhould be miſtaken, by judging him according to our ſelves, he gives us to know,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.7, 8, 9.</note> that <hi>his thoughts are not as our thoughts, nor his ways like our ways;</hi> low, narrow, and ſhort: <hi>But as the heavens are high above the earth, ſo are his ways and thoughts high above our ways.</hi> A compariſon large and wide enough, to ſhew us the vaſt diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt Finite and Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now there can be nothing more ſuitable and agreeable to the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Bounty, Wiſdom, Power, and Juſtice of his Eſſence, which is Infinite, than a Deſign, that all his Creatures ſhould be happy according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral capacities, which he, who made
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60064:69"/>nothing in vain, created them with. And on the contrary, to ſuppoſe he made any thing with a capacity of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying any degree of Happineſs, as its ultimate End, and chief Good; and yet with an intention and deſign, not onely of not attaining it, but of being for ever miſerable, is ſo far from mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying his Goodneſs or Juſtice, that it would argue him of ſuch a cruel na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as were the higheſt derogation, and moſt proper blaſphemy, to believe it of him. And that his Juſtice will be glorified in the puniſhment and miſery of ſome of his Creatures, even of the Nobleſt Rank, he aſſures us with the higheſt proteſtation imaginable, is far from being an effect of his Will, and is perfectly occaſioned by their own choice, and wilful folly. <hi>As I live, ſaith the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> that is, as ſurely as I am, <hi>I have no pleaſure in the death of a ſinner, but had rather that he ſhould turn and live. Turn ye, turn ye; why will ye die?</hi> And if he has no pleaſure in his death, a ſmaller puniſhment, undoubtedly not in his Eternal Damnation, the greateſt of all miſeries.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, let us conſider, That
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60064:69"/>the ſcope of all Religion, and the Commands of God in Scripture, all aim directly at this White; <hi>viz.</hi> the happineſs of all Mankind, even here in this Life, in order to an Eternal Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs hereafter, in the Life of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and Glory: and therefore does ſo frequently promiſe to the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent all thoſe things, which may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the happineſs even of this Life; the <hi>Bona Corporis Animi &amp; Fortunae,</hi> all the good things of Body, and Mind, and Eſtate; according to that ſaying of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.6. 1 Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Godlineſs with content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (which it onely can give) <hi>is great gain, having the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> Now the means which God commands us to uſe, and the means which he directs, are the moſt certain Rule for us to make a Judgment, what is the End at which he would have us arrive. For God is true, and cannot lie, though all men may be liars, and therefore we are bound to believe him; and that he cannot tell us one thing, when he means another directly contrary to it: as ſome men, who call themſelves Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, have both by Word and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60064:70"/>publickly avowed, and publiſh'd to the World.</p>
               <p>If we look upon the Commands of the Law, ſuch as were not onely par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation in their Typical Service, but common to all the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by Faith; we ſhall find, that they all aim at this: And the Two Tables, written with the Divine Characters, by the immediate Finger of God, direct, firſt, his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſecondly, man's happineſs, by obedience to Superiours, in the firſt Commandment with promiſe; by Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Chaſtity, Temperance, Truth, and Honeſty, and all other Virtues, which conduce to our happineſs here in this Life: and by making us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Divine Nature, fitting and preparing us for the enjoyment of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Happineſs hereafter.</p>
               <p>And if we examine either the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or Practiſe of all holy Men, ſo far as their Practiſe is recorded for our example, we ſhall find, that they have all a tendency to theſe very Ends.</p>
               <p>If we come to look into that <hi>Royal Law of Liberty,</hi> the Goſpel, we ſhall find, that all its Commands and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:60064:70"/>lead us to our own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: witneſs that Golden, and, even by Heathens, much celebrated Rule, of our bleſſed Jeſus, <hi>To do to all men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 7.12.</note> 
                  <hi>as we would that they ſhould do unto us.</hi> A Rule to make all the World happy, and a Rule which, I am ſure, no Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter dare abide by, and which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth all that ever went before it, and is the higheſt exaltation of Humane Nature, even to ſuch a degree, as brings it to a near affinity and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the bleſſed Divinity,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.44, <hi>ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
                  </note> who makes his <hi>Sun to ſhine upon the juſt and unjuſt.</hi> To <hi>love our enemies.</hi> To <hi>bleſs thoſe that curſe us,</hi> to <hi>do good to them that hate us,</hi> and to <hi>pray for them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe us and perſecute us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Diſciples ſpake the ſame Language of their great Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who left his Peace, and command of Unity, to <hi>love one another,</hi> as a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy among them; and enforces it upon them with the moſt powerful perſuaſive, <hi>If ye love me, keep my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.15.</note> telling them, this love and unity ſhould be the badge and diſtinction of their profeſſion,<note place="margin">Joh. 13.35.</note> 
                  <hi>By this ſhall all men know that you are my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:60064:71"/>if ye love one another.</hi> Thus there fore they command Piety and Unity, Peace and Charity, Love unfeigned, Obedience to Magiſtrates and Miniſters; that Duty, Honour, and Reſpect, which is due to any, to be given unto them: to live Juſtly, Soberly, Religiouſly in this preſent World; in all Honeſty, Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs, Humility, Chaſtity, Temperance, and all other Virtues and Goodneſs, one toward another, and as we have opportunity to do good unto all. Let any man judge, if theſe Rules were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly followed, if the Golden Age would not return, and all men be as happy as heart can wiſh. The Effects which they would produce, plainly demonſtrate the Ends for which they were deſigned.</p>
               <p>Beſides, all agree to this, That the great deſign of the Creation was the glory of the Creator; now the ſame thing which glorifies the Creator, does alſo make the Creature happy; and that is, Obedience to his Will, Laws, and Commands. And that the Will of God is to be glorified by the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and not Puniſhment of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as his firſt deſign in their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:60064:71"/>has already, from his own proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, been ſhewn. And the Apoſtle is as plain as poſitive in this point, That <hi>God would have all men to be ſaved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.3,4. ver. 6.</note> by <hi>coming to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> And for this purpoſe, that <hi>Chriſt gave himſelf a ranſome for all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whoſoever does peruſe the holy Goſpel, ſhall be forced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that the whole deſign of it is, That all men, by the knowledge of God, and of Jeſus Chriſt, might come to yield obedience to his holy Laws and Directions; and that by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> they <hi>might eſcape the polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and corruptions that is in the world through luſt;</hi> and be made <hi>partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi> by living juſtly, righteouſly, and Godlike, blameleſs and harmleſs, as the Sons of God here in this world: that ſo through the all-ſufficient merits and ſatisfaction of the onely Son of God, they may, as the end of their Faith, Hope, Charity, and Conſtancy, be made partakers of that glorious Life and Immortality, which he has purchaſed for them with his moſt precious Bloud.</p>
               <p>So that as nothing can be more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:60064:72"/>to the excellency of the Divine Being, than a deſign in their Creation, that they ſhould all be happy accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeveral Capacities; ſo nothing is more clear, from the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent and deſign of the Holy Scriptures, which contain the Will of God, than that this was the great and ultimate End of the <hi>Omnipotent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> in the framing the World, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in the Creation of Mankind, to be happy both here and hereafter in a future ſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:60064:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Some neceſſary Corollaries from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſcourſe; with the Concluſion, to all men to endeavour after Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FRom what has before been ſaid, we may draw theſe neceſſary and practical Conſequences and Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That every man is obliged to yield obedience to Conſcience, upon pain of Eternal Damnation: becauſe every man is obliged, under that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, to walk according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Rule, which is that by which Conſcience judges every man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he does right or wrong: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what St. <hi>John</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>If our heart,</hi> that is, our Conſcience, <hi>condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things,</hi> and moſt certainly will condemn us in that great and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgment-day. And whoſoever vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olates a known command of Scripture, however he may colour it over with the fair pretence of Religion, yet, as
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60064:73"/>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Though the truth of God ſhould abound, through my lie, unto his glory, yet I ſhall be alſo judged as a ſinner.</hi> And ſo ſhall all thoſe, who with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of advancing God's glory and the truth, act contrary to the Rule of Truth and Righteouſneſs. But if at the laſt it ſhall be found, that they have not been managed by Conſcience, but Opinion and Perſuaſion, what can they expect, but the greateſt ſeverities, and inſufferable torments and agonies of Conſcience, <hi>the worm that never dies?</hi> which ſhould put all men upon a ſtrict examination of themſelves, eſpecially thoſe who pretend to be ſo much man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged by Conſcience; whether it be a true and good Conſcience, or onely theſe Deceivers and Uſurpers, <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Perſuaſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it follows, That Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things in Religious Worſhip, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no further Obligation upon mens Conſciences, than as they conduce to God's glory, and the happineſs of the Univerſe; and a Lawful Authority having a Power to put a final deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination upon every man's private Judgment and Opinion, by declaring
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60064:73"/>which of all theſe indifferent things they judge moſt conducive to God's glory, and the happineſs of all thoſe under their Juriſdiction, by promoting and preſerving Peace, Unity, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Therefore that all perſons who live under their Authority, are bound in Conſcience to ſubmit to thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations: and from thence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to eſteem that, which before was in its own nature indifferent, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neceſſary: becauſe hereby many known Duties, and particularly that of Obedience to Magiſtrates (without which, there can be no happineſs on Earth) are performed, to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of an abſolute and indiſpenſible Obligation of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it follows, That all men are bound in Conſcience to promote and endeavour the well-being of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Government under which they live; and, as much as in them lies, the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all Mankind even here in this life. Nor can they follow the Dictates of true Religion or Conſcience, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may pretend or imagine, who for their private Opinions, make Parties, break Laws, deſpiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60064:74"/>give diſturbances to the Peace and Security of their Native Countrey at home, and by promoting Faction, Diſſention, and Diviſion, give encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to our Enemies abroad. And by too juſt fears, from what has been, of what may be again, by the ſame ways and artifices, to make mens minds uneaſie, and their lives unhappy. And ſhould their Deſigns ſucceed a ſecond time, to involve ſo many millions in the calamities of War, Confuſion, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and Deſolation.</p>
               <p>Theſe have been, and are the proper effects of Diſobedience to Laws and Lawful Authority: and let all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters look well to it, for they will find, here is no Conſcience, no Religion to be found in ſuch ways and ends, to which their Separation and Diviſion do moſt infallibly lead them.</p>
               <p>I wiſh I could conclude this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with the moſt perſuaſive Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and irreſiſtable Reaſon. That all Chriſtian People, and eſpecially thoſe Diſſenters of theſe Nations, would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider with themſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Diſcords and Differences about Religious affairs will in the end
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:60064:74"/>lead them; and in time turn back again, before they come to the diſmal brink of thoſe Precipices, Miſery here, and Damnation hereafter; which when by a too late Repentance they would avoid, they will not be able.</p>
               <p>I wiſh they would no longer abuſe that glorious name of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to countenance thoſe Irreligious practiſes, of Diſobedience, Uncharitableneſs, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention and Separation.</p>
               <p>Let them conſider, what it is in this World that is moſt deſirable; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do not act point blank con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own Intereſt and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both here and hereafter; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the publick Good of the Community of which they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and whether they may not juſtly fear, that by theſe dangerous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful practices, they ſhould ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate Authority, as to exerciſe its utmoſtrigors and ſeverities upon them, as being out of all hopes to reclaim them by gentle means, and juſtly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their malicious, ſecret, and ill deſigns, in reality againſt the State, though the pretence be onely againſt the preſent Church and its Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:60064:75"/>
               <p>Let them conſider, that if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have peace within their private Walls, and plenteouſneſs within their ſtately Palaces; if they deſire to enjoy quiet of mind at home, tranquility, peace, and unity one amongſt another; that <hi>Justice ſhould run down as a River, and Righteouſneſs us a mighty Stream.</hi> That <hi>Truth ſhould ſpring out of the Earth, and Righteouſneſs look down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> That <hi>Mercy and Truth ſhould meet together, Righteouſneſs and Peace ſhould kiſs each other; and that glory may dwell in our Land.</hi> If they deſire to be ſafe from inteſtine and domeſtick troubles, ſecure from Forreign force and invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: to be loved, reſpected, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by their Friends and Allies; dreaded by their greateſt Enemies; to be great in Riches, great in Fame, and greater in all Goodneſs and Virtue, to be the joy and glory of all Lands. If they deſire theſe, there is no way to obtain them, but by uniting our ſelves with this common Bond, and indiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble Chain of a good Conſcience, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and all men: which will teach every man his duty; keep every man quietly, peaceably, and contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60064:75"/>in his place and ſtation; and ſecure unto us all thoſe dear Delights of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, Peace, Property, and Religion. If they deſire theſe, thus muſt they endeavour after them; and if they will not endeavour after them, we cannot but judge, that they do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire them. And I am ſure, if they do not deſire theſe bleſſings, both for themſelves and all others, they neither deſerve them, nor any love, pity, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, countenance or kindneſs; but ought to be look'd upon, not as men, but fierce and ſavage Beaſts, Wolves, Tigers, and Bears, given to Prey, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, and Ravage; and they may eaſily gheſs what will follow, if once they come to be look'd upon and eſteemed ſuch.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if they have any love or kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their Souls, or ever hope for eternal Salvation, it muſt not be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without obedience to God, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Government, and obedience to Conſcience.</p>
               <p>After all this I will hope that thoſe happy days will ſhine upon us,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122, 3.</note> in which we may ſay, <hi>Our</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is built as a City that is compact, or at unity with it
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60064:76"/>ſelf:</hi> And that we ſhall be able to ſing that glorious and triumphant Song of Praiſe and Thankſgiving,<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed in the City of our God, in the mountain of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. Beautiful for ſituation, the joy of the whole earth is Mount</hi> Zion <hi>on the ſides of the North the City of the great King. God is well known in her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces as a ſure Refuge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To haſten which bleſſed and happy Age, let every good Chriſtian lay to his helping hand, and his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart, by endeavouring to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of the great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which is the great Concern and Intereſt of every Man, both in reference to Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs here and hereafter, <hi>Keeping alwayes a Conſcience void of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence towards God, and towards all Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:60064:76"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
